you know when I give the cash paid
Rosetta Thornton came from Tacoma I'm
gonna switch to English since we have
since Jordan hasn't had dr. Peterson
hasn't had time to learn enough
Icelandic yet so thank you all for
coming this has been amazing first when
I got the idea to book him to Iceland I
had no idea that others had been
watching him on YouTube so as it turns
out a lot of people have been and of
course he's exploded since then in in
popularity so we've sold out this venue
which is almost three times larger than
the first one we had and we've sold it
out two times so that's pretty good
so he's gonna come up here and he's
gonna speak for one hour and 15 minutes
just about then he's gonna take a four
minute break and go offstage before the
Q&A you can submit questions to the Q&A
and we're gonna use a similar system
that he's been using on his trips in
America with Dave Rubin so I'm gonna
serve as a surrogate Dave Rubin here or
slightly less gay Dave Rubin so and I'll
bring I'll ask him the questions and you
will put them online on a site called
slide oh so it's spelled SLI dot do
slide though I'll say it in Icelandic as
well as at a punter Dao Slater so it is
customary to introduce the speaker as if
you know me better than him but and and
usually when someone is being introduced
people tell things about him things that
are true about that speaker now of
course you've all come here because you
know who that guy is but so and I'm
gonna do a different thing because I
think it has tells you more deeply
something about what is going on with
this guy so I'm going to read you a few
things that are wrong about him so these
are actual things that have been said
about him in media mostly in hit pieces
and you know character assassination
attempts and there has been one each day
just about for a long time and some of
them in big big media so he's a he's a
far-right guy Hitler he wants to force
young women in Toomer
he's the stupid people's smart person
that's actually not that bad about him
but so and that's the reason they say
that they want you to become afraid to
admit that you like him or go to his
talks well-groomed all right
at least he's well-groomed a messiah
comes surrogate dad for gormless dimwits
so that's another one directed at you I
I'm one of you as well because I don't
know what gormless means so but I
suspect that having a gourmet is
preferable so just stay away from this
guy
Tim wits Jordan Peterson has nothing of
value to say he's a patriarchal
pseudoscientist he encourages young men
to see themselves as victims
he's a mash-up of he has he delivers a
mash-up of Cosmo tips and my first book
of myths he's the professor of piffle he
seems like a terrible therapist he's a
bad political and social thinker an
angry white guy and the line between
Peterson's authoritarianism and Richard
Spencer's Paley on Nazism is a blurry
one he's a Jewish shill and if you're
gonna be a shield you you you want to be
a Jew issue and he's a fascist miss mist
assist and this is just a small sample
of what has been going on and it's all
wrong perhaps you know depending on how
you define she'll-she'll can Sheila's
okay but it's all wrong and that tells
you something a new one every day too
miss inform people about that man and
you can demonstrate it it's demonstrably
false everything and there are some
people that see him as a risk to their
agenda and their world we
HBU for some reason but he's a he's a
reasonable balanced moderate truthful
man and I've never seen such a campaign
against any thinker ever in the world
not even someone that is untruthful or
as despicable as they make him sound
like so this tells you something this is
the reason I was reading this this tells
you something about the importance of
his message and I'm not gonna I'm not
gonna theorize about exactly what that
is because there are lots of theories
about exactly what it is in what he's
saying that is threatening and and to
whom it is threatening and and I think
actually many of them are correct but
let's just listen to him and let's hear
what he has to say
and we'll figure out why it's
threatening later so please give a warm
welcome to dr. Jordan B Peterson
[Applause]
well that's an introduction that I'm
going to have to live up to so I was mmm
thinking the other day about numbers you
know there are mathematicians who think
that there isn't anything more real than
numbers and that's an interesting
proposition I mean it's obviously the
case that once you invent or discover
numbers that that confers on you a
tremendous power and who knows the
limits of that power and the claim that
numbers are more real than anything else
is predicated in part on the fact that
when you discover them or invent them
and start to utilize them that your
ability to operate in the world expands
immensely and and so that's one of the
ways of judging whether or not something
is real is whether or not when you use
it that facilitates your means of
operating in the world interestingly
numbers are abstractions and so that
raises another question which is well
what's more real the thing that's being
abstracted from or the abstractions and
again that's not obvious and maybe the
question of more real isn't germane
maybe it's a question of equal reality
but it's not obvious that abstractions
aren't real and you can make a damn
strong case that they're more real than
anything else and so then you might ask
yourself well then what are the most
real abstractions and so that's what I'm
going to start to talk about tonight I'm
going to talk about it in relationship
to as many rules as I can
lay out simultaneously I'll go through
the rules first
so rule 1 is stand up straight with your
shoulders back and rule 2 is treat
yourself like you're someone responsible
for helping on number 3 which is very
tightly associated with number 2 they're
sort of variations on a theme is make
friends with those people who want the
best for you and by the way these last
two rules aren't injunctions designed to
make your life easier they're actually
injunctions designed to make your life
more difficult Kierkegaard said at one
point that his role in life given that
everything was proceeding to become
easier and easier in all possible ways
that there would come a time when people
would cry out for difficulty and so
that's partly how he envisioned his role
in the world interestingly enough as a
universal benefactor of mankind who
would strive to do nothing other than to
make life more difficult for everyone
right and so rule two and three are like
that because treat yourself as if you're
someone responsible for helping isn't
the same as be nice to yourself it's not
that and to associate with people who
want the best for you means that they
get to demand the best from you and
that's also not an easy thing rule 4 is
compare yourself to who you were
yesterday and not to who someone else is
today and that's an injunction about
envy right it's easy you need people who
you need things that are above you
because you need to do something
worthwhile with your life you need
something to aim at but one of the
consequences of that is that you can
become envious of people that you
believe have attained more in a deserve
adore undeserved manner and that can
make you bitter and so it's much better
to compare yourself to yourself and to
use yourself as the target for
improvement in comparison rule 5 is
don't let your children do anything that
makes you dislike them and the rule of
thumb there is if you dislike them then
other people will and it's a bad idea
to allow your children to act in a way
that makes other children dislike them
or adults dislike them given that
they're going to have to deal with
children and they're going to have to
deal with adults so your primary
responsibility as a parent is to help
your child learn how to behave so that
the social world opens up its arms to
them and welcomes them at every level
and you've done your job if you can
manage that and it's not a simple thing
to do
rule six is put your house in perfect
order before you criticize the world and
that's not take no action for others
until you have your act together that
isn't what the rule means it means that
bind your ambition with humility and
work on what's right in front of you
that you will suffer for if you get
wrong before you engage in the
large-scale transformation of other
people rule seven is do what is
meaningful and not what is expedient and
I would say in some sense in some sense
that's the core ethos of the book not
exactly because rule eight which is tell
the truth or at least don't lie is a
necessary conjunction to that or a
necessary additional element because I
don't think that you can pursue what is
meaningful without telling the truth and
the reason for that is if you don't tell
the truth or let's say if you lie which
is an easier way to think about it you
corrupt the mechanisms the instinctual
mechanisms that that that manifest
themselves as meaning and then you can't
trust them and that's a very bad idea
so the fundamental reason to not lie is
because you corrupt your own perceptions
if you lie and when you corrupt your own
perceptions then you can't rely on
yourself and if you can't rely on
yourself then well good luck to you
because what are you going to rely on in
the absence of your own judgment here
you've got nothing if you if you lose
that rule rule eight is as I said tell
the truth they're doing
or at least don't lie rule 9 assume that
the person that you're listening to
knows something you don't
and that's not so much a mark of respect
for the person although it is that it's
a mark of recognition of your own
unbearable ignorance you know one of the
things you have to do in life is decide
whether you're more you have to make
friends more with let me see let me just
let me rephrase that properly you have
to decide what's more important what you
know or what you don't know first of all
there's a lot of what you don't know and
so if you make friends with that if you
decide that's important then well that's
a good thing because you're going to be
surrounded by what you don't know your
entire life and so if you're
appreciative of that then that's going
to make things go better for you but but
the other element of that is well why
should you be appreciative of what you
don't know and answer to that is well
you shouldn't if your life is absolutely
perfect in every way you have exactly
what you need and want you've put
everything in order around you then what
you know is sufficient but if you
believe that things could still be put
right around you in your own personal
life and with regard to the effect that
you have on other people then obviously
what you don't yet know is more
important than what you do know and you
should be paying attention to find out
what you don't know at every possible
moment and if you're fortunate when you
have a conversation with someone and
you're actually interested in what they
say then even if they're not very good
at communicating even if they're awkward
or even if they display a certain amount
of enmity towards you there's always the
possibility that they might tell you
something you don't know in which case
you can walk away from the conversation
less ignorant and corrupt than you were
when you started the conversation and if
your life isn't everything that you
would like it to be then being slightly
less ignorant and corrupt is probably a
good thing and so rule 10 is be precise
in your speech and that's that's an
observation I would say that that's a
variant
of a New Testament injunction which is
or maybe a description of the nature of
the world which is knock and the door
will open and ask and you will receive
which is a very strange theory let's say
but which I would say is far more in
accordance with what we know about the
psychology of perception let's say then
you might imagine because it is the case
that you don't get what you don't aim at
you might get what you do aim at and
your aim might get better as you aim as
well which is something to consider if
you specify the nature of the actually
if you specify the nature of the being
that you want to bring into being then
you radically increase the probability
that that's what will occur and of
course you all know that because you
regard yourself at least to some degree
as active creative agents right your
fundamental attitude towards yourself at
least in the manner that you act towards
yourself is that you wake up in the
morning and you have a landscape of
possibilities that lay themselves open
to you and you make choices between
those possibilities and determine in
consequence how the world is going to
manifest itself so you confront a field
of potential that's a good way of
thinking about it and through your
choices you determine which elements of
that potential are going to concretize
them selves into the real world and you
are very unhappy with yourself if you
don't do that properly and you're very
unhappy with other people if they don't
do that properly and you're very unhappy
with other people if they don't treat
you like that's what you're like because
part of what you demand from people
let's say in terms of sheer civility is
that they act towards you is if you're
the locus of voluntary choice in a world
of potential and you upbraid each other
for that as well if you have children
and parents your parents will say to you
if you're fortunate you're not living up
to your potential which is actually a
compliment in a sense even though it's
also
a judgment and the compliment is I know
perfectly well that you could be more
than you are and you'll hang your head
if you have any sense and you'll think
like you think in relationship to your
own conscience that yes I have a lot of
potential that I'm not fully realizing
and that actually constitutes a
transgression against the good and I
don't I don't think I've ever met anyone
who doesn't believe that if you if you
have a reasonable conversation with them
it just seems self-evident
I mean maybe now and then you meet
someone who's narcissistically
self-satisfied but then they're
narcissistic and that's not good that as
a medium to long term strategy that's a
catastrophe that ends in disaster you
know it's a short term it protects
people but long term it's it's not good
in the least and of course other people
don't appreciate it as well rule 11 is
don't bother children when they're
skateboarding and that's actually a
discussion of courage of encouragement
more specifically because I've I've been
trying to understand for example what
role parents play in the lives of their
children and I would say this is a role
that that that is of fundamental
importance as well as attempting to
guide your children so that they act in
a socially desirable manner so that the
world opens itself up to them you also
want to encourage them which is not the
same as sheltering them it's not the
same at all and to encourage someone is
to say something like or to act out
something like look kid as you the
world's already difficult because the
world isn't easy for children any more
than it's easy for adults that the
difficulties are they're not the same
they're child size difficulties but
they're still difficulties the world is
a very hard place and it's a bitter
place in many ways and it's not only a
hard and bitter place it's also touched
with betrayal and malevolence and that's
the fundamental bottom line but there's
something in you that is capable of
taking that full-on and transcending it
and that's encouragement you say well as
difficult as things are
you're up to the challenge and to
interfere with children when they're
skateboarding for example when they're
doing let's say in advisably dangerous
things which kids of course do if
they're skateboarding to interfere with
that is to interfere with the child's
willingness to voluntarily expose
themselves to the risks that they need
to expose themselves to in order to
develop the sort of competence that
allows them to thrive in a world they
cannot be sheltered from and so to
interfere with children when they're
taking necessary risks is not love or
empathy but cowardice on the part of
parents and it's deeply damaging to
children and I can tell you as a
clinical psychologist I've never had a
client come to my office in all the
hundreds in in in all the hundreds of
encounters I've had with people in my
office I've never had a client say my
parents made me too independent right
that hasn't happened once right now my
parents made me too dependent or I
conspired with my parents to perpetuate
my dependence that happened all the time
so there's a rule of thumb which I think
is a good one which I believe is often
applied in nursing homes by people who
work in nursing homes which is of course
a very difficult job and the rule is do
not do anything for anyone they can do
for themselves and the reason for that
is that it's a form of theft right you
don't first of all if you if you do
something for someone and it facilitates
their movement forward then they moved
forward because you helped them which is
something I was very careful about as a
therapist I don't want to give my
clients advice first it might fail in
which case they are going to pay for my
advice and second if it succeeds then I
get to be the successful one and I don't
want to steal the success from my
clients that's a bad idea I want to help
them figure out what it is that they
should aim at and then help plot out a
strat
for attaining that and but I want to
ensure that it's their destiny not
something I'm imposing and of course the
imposition of that sort of thing is the
hallmark of a bad I would say
therapeutic relationship but also a bad
relationship period right so one of the
things you want to do with your
partner's your spouse you say your
husband or wife and also with your
children is to listen to them so that
you can figure out what their problems
are and figure out with them because
they're gonna figure that out by
communicating and then perhaps aid them
in the development of a strategy but you
have to ensure very carefully that
you're not imposing your own structure
in a manner that's going to steal from
them what's rightfully theirs so well so
rule 11 is an injunction to courage as
the fundamental because you could say
well what's the antidote to the
catastrophe of life and one answer might
be safety it's like well you know look
everyone sensible enough to know that a
certain amount of provision for safety
is worthwhile you should probably wear
your seatbelts when you're driving
around in your car because why take
foolhardy risks but given that there is
no security in life in the final
analysis then encouragement is a much
better medication than sheltering and so
and that's what that's that's I think in
keeping with the idea that what life is
essentially is not a place to attain
happiness or even to aim for happiness
even though you should be grateful if
some comes along now and then but a call
to something like adventure and I think
that's the proper way of conceptualizing
it certainly if you go watch a story a
movie you read a book something like
that if you encounter a narrative that's
gripping whether it's a romance or a
classic adventure story then the element
of it that's gripping is the adventure
and so to portray life as an adventure
in romance and and in the world is the
proper way to portray it and the way
that you facilitate the adventure is
encouragement I had a client once I
really liked him he was a good guy his
smart guy good-looking young guy had
everything going for him you know he's a
good musician he was a talented athlete
but he hadn't been encouraged I wouldn't
say he told me about his relationship
with his girlfriend he said his
girlfriend wanted to go biking around
southern Ontario she was about 19 or 20
and he thought he might join her and
when she went and talked to her parents
they made every provision possible to
help her prepare for the journey to make
sure her bike was in good shape to make
sure she had the right equipment to help
her plot out a route and when he went
and talked to his parents all they did
was worry that he was going to get hurt
and like he might get hurt because
people get hurt but they didn't
understand that they were choosing
between the hurt that he might encounter
by going out in the world and having an
adventure let's say with his girlfriend
or the hurt that he would encounter by
staying at home cowering in his basement
under the protection of his over loving
parents while his girlfriend ventured
bravely into the world you think well
which of those two things is most likely
to be damaging and the answer to that is
well his parents wouldn't worry as much
as if he was in the basement and that's
the wrong worry even because they should
worry more not less so in rule 12 is pet
a cat when you encounter one on the
street and it's a oddly enough a
meditation on fragility it's a
discussion of what you do when you don't
know what to do and that's really when
things have gone badly for you when you
face a terrible tragedy in your own
personal life or in your familial life
or perhaps even in life of your
community when things come crowding in
ant you too quickly in the case of a
death in the family or a terrible
illness or the collapse of a dream or
any of the things that can flip your
world upside down is how do you cope
with that and that chapter contains
discussion of
the necessity of narrowing your
timeframe you know because sometimes the
right way to look at the world is across
years and sometimes it's across months
and when things are more out of control
perhaps it's across days and when things
are really when you're really up against
the wall its acro across hours or even
minutes and during those minutes then
you concentrate on doing as well as you
can with what's right in front of you
for the longest unit of time that you
can tolerate conceptualizing maybe
that's what you do at someone's deathbed
and while you're doing that and
suffering away madly then you also take
the time to appreciate everything you
can that manifests itself that allows
itself to be appreciated and so that's
the metaphor of the cat I suppose and so
that's the 12 rules and I'll return to
rule one which is stand up straight with
your shoulders back and I'm going to use
it as a platform for laying out the
abstractions that I talk to at the
beginning of the lecture so some of you
might be familiar with the central
Taoist symbol and it's a symbol of Dow
and Dow is a very strange word it
doesn't have an easily translatable
single meaning at least in English it
means a variety of things that means the
path of life so that would mean the the
path that you take as you move forward
through life but it would mean more also
the proper path so it's that it's the
proper path through life so the idea now
is a symbol of reality and one of the
things that means is the path you take
through life and so there's an implicit
idea there that the fundamental reality
of life is the path you take through
life it's not a materialist idea it's a
different kind of idea it's the idea
that life is a journey
while we're mobile creatures and we're
on a journey and the best way to
conceptualize reality is as the place
that you journey through and the
question is well what are the elements
what are the constituent elements of the
place that you journey through because
that's also part of Dao and the Daoists
believe that that's yin and yang and ian
is the black serpent because those are
two serpents head-to-head that make up
the totality of the world and the black
serpent is yin
and yen is feminine classically speaking
from the Taoist perspective it's a
symbolic representation doesn't mean
that women are yen and that men men
aren't it's not that it's an attempt to
use sexual symbolism to represent a
deeper underlying reality and yang is
masculine yin is dark and Knight and
there's a white dot in the black serpent
and there's a black dot in the white
surf and the white serpent is the
daytime and masculinity and it's the
interplay between those two things that
make up reality and one can transform
into the other at any moment and so
that's the taoist idea of reality and so
there's yin and yang and they make up
the world and the question is perhaps
our question is well what exactly does
that mean
well it actually means something it's a
kind of abstraction and it's actually an
incredibly helpful abstraction once you
understand the abstraction it might be
the most real abstraction there is so
I'm going to lay out a little bit I'll
lay out for you a little bit about what
these two domains refer to and then I'm
going to make a case that they're real
and then I'm going to tell you what it
means that they're real
so you could think of Yin as chaos now
we need to know what chaos is no chaos
is what God made the world out of at the
beginning of time so one of the things
that chaos is is it's something like
potential and so you can imagine and
this is not how we think as modern
people because we tend to think in a
materialist way but it is how we act and
as I said already you act as if you
confront potential and you treat
potential level as if it's real and if
your attitude towards it confers on you
a certain moral obligation which is why
you know what people mean when they say
you're not living up to your potential
no one ever says well what do you mean
by potential not unless they're being
argumentative because you already know
and very few people say while I'm fully
living up to my potential so you admit
to the
reality that undergirds that conception
that makes that question a possibility
immediately the potential is while
potential is the future that's part of
it and we believe in the future we
believe that it exists even though it
isn't here and it's not measurable it's
it only exists as a potential set of
realizable possibilities that's what the
future is and it's really what we
contend with we don't really contend
with the present precisely we orient
ourselves towards the future and the
future comes at us from every direction
and we we decide as we encounter the
future which parts of it we're going to
interact with and how we're going to
construct the present and the past as a
consequence of doing that and so part of
chaos is potential and that's the
positive part it's like if you're in a
bind what you look for is potential is
there another way of conceptualizing
this do I have a different way of acting
can I make another plan is there
something that I'm not taking into
account that would make this terrible
situation tolerable that's all an
attempt to to call upon potential and to
use it to transfigure a reality that's
intolerable and maybe it's intolerable
because of the way you're
conceptualizing it now I'm not being
naive about that I understand perfectly
well that people can find themselves so
badly cornered in life that they're
basically done no matter what they do
people obviously develop fatal illnesses
and and they die and and their
businesses collapse and genuinely
terrible things can happen to you that
aren't your fault that you can't fix I'm
not saying that you can just gerrymander
the world by changing your attitude it's
not that straightforward
but I am saying that you have a
tremendous ability to transform the
landscape of possibility that reveals
itself in front of you and that when
things are terrible that's your best bet
it doesn't mean it will succeed
it just means you don't have a better
option and so chaos that potential is
also something that manifests itself
a terrible manner so imagine this this
is a good way of thinking about it
it's imagine that you have a an intimate
relationship let's let's say a marriage
and the marriage is predicated on trust
and fidelity which is a variant of trust
and that the trust and fidelity is an
axiom of your memories you might think
well what does that mean it's like well
let's play it out imagine you've been
married for 10 years and then your wife
tells you that she has had three affairs
each of them lasted three years and the
last one has lasted five years and it's
still ongoing
or maybe you discover that okay so then
you might say well what happens then
well what happens is that everything you
thought was wrong right and this is such
an interesting thing because it actually
means you had the past and you think the
past is fixed it's done with that's why
it's the past but all of a sudden you
find out that one of the things that you
thought about the past and it happens to
be a very important thing wasn't true at
all and so what that means is that whole
past that you thought was what it was
wasn't what it was at all and so it
transforms itself from an actuality
into potential and most of that
potential is negative and unless you're
relieved that your wife had an affair
well but that's an important
consideration because you know you could
imagine a situation where your marriage
is dreadfully unhappy and you're just
looking for an excuse to leave it's
possible that that revelation even
though it would be shocking would also
come with a fair bit of relief and so
this potent the potential that manifests
itself even when it's unexpected doesn't
only necessarily manifest itself in a
negative guys it can also free you you
know and and if your marriage was
unhappy even if you wanted to cling to
it if your marriage wasn't happy and the
betrayal was revealed and you're
divorced and you set yourself up in two
years you might be in a better place
than you were it's not a pathway I'm
recommending by the way I'm just saying
that it's more complicated than that
look
that's the introduction of chaos into
order right and the the the oldest story
we have is something like order is
susceptible to disruption by chaos and
the human that the fundamental demand
that's made on the human being is to
contend with the chaos that disrupts
order not to live in order and not to
live in chaos but to be able to contend
with the chaos that disrupts order and
so when you encourage your children for
example what you're doing is encouraging
them to become the Masters of the chaos
that can disrupt order rather than
denizens of order which makes them
tyrants or denizens of chaos which makes
them nihilistic and hopeless so you
train your children you encourage your
children and yourself and your partner
if you have any sense to be a master of
emergent chaos and to be able to contend
with that and so so chaos is potential
and it's this disruptive it's the
capacity of the infinite world to
disrupt your finite considerations
that's another way of looking at it
another way of looking at it is it's the
serpent in the Garden of Eden and the
reason that that story is set up the way
it is is because it's trying to
represent that there's no place that's
so bounded and secure even if it's set
up by God himself that doesn't have an
agent of chaos inside it it's exactly
the same idea that the Dallas put
forward with their with their symbolic
representation
it's just portrayed in a different
manner and the question is well what do
you do in the garden given that there's
a snake in it and the answer to that is
something like you've become the master
of snakes and so and that's a deep idea
that's the same idea as confronting the
dragon and getting the treasure that's
the same idea as going to the bottom of
the ocean and rescuing your father from
the belly of the whale it's the same
idea and that's an element in the
greatest of stories and the greatest of
stories is heroic
Roark's story and the heroic story is to
voluntarily confront the unknown when it
manifests itself and to gather something
of value as a consequence and to share
it with the community there isn't a
story that's more emblematic of what it
means to be human than that that that is
us that's our best bet
alright so chaos chaos is the
catastrophe that will suddenly enter
your life chaos is the flood that's
definitely coming chaos is the
ever-present possibility of apocalypse
in your personal life in your familial
life and in this broader social life
right chaos is the consequence of your
finite fragility existing in a world
that's beyond you chaos is potential
chaos is what lies before you chaos is
what you can call on when you need
something to rescue yourself from
malfunctioning order it's a permanent
element of existence chaos is what you
don't know chaos is what's outside the
fire chaos is what's outside the walls
of your house chaos is what's outside
the walls of your town chaos is what's
outside of the borders of your country
all of that is chaos and potential order
order is where you are when what you're
doing is working in the manner that you
intended okay it's a very specific
definition how do you know that you know
what you're doing well you don't because
you don't know what you're doing because
you don't know everything everything you
do is bounded by ignorance well you
still have to operate in the world and
so what you do is you make finite plans
and the new execute plans and then you
execute strategies to to make those
plans manifest themselves and if the
plans manifest themselves the way that
you desired then you regard your
knowledge as sufficient that's your
definition of truth and it's the only
definition of truth that you can use
because you don't have everything at
hand and when you're where what you're
doing is working that's order and you
might think well I should just stay
there because that's a comfortable place
to be
and there's a certain amount of truth to
that except for one thing
if you've defined a domain of order and
you stand in it and you wait the
disorder will enter all by itself
because things aren't static things
change all the time and your attempt to
bind yourself within a static structure
is destined to fail because everything
around you is in flux and the thing that
you've parceled out as permanent will
transform itself across time here's an
example let's say you're a perfectly
well adapted eleven-year-old and it's
actually possible to meet it 11 year old
children are often very delightful
because they're like adult children
they're not teenagers they're like as
they're they're the most mature form of
children and they can be really
delightful people and then like three
years later you hate them and and the
reason for that is that of course as
soon as they hit puberty which is the
emergence of chaos into the into the
already developed childhood structures
really the emergence of sexuality into a
structure that didn't have to adapt to
sexuality and maybe even the emergence
of aggression to some degree but mostly
sexuality if the child maintains only
the 11-year old personality by the time
they're 16 they're no longer a
delightful 11 year old there are very
immature 16 year old and the reason that
I'm pointing that out is because just
because something works for you now
doesn't mean it's going to work for you
five years from now and so in order to
remain stable you can't be stagnant
they're not the same thing
stability is a dynamic not a not
something static and so not only do you
have to be where you are
but you have to be going to where you're
going and you have to be participating
in both of those things actively so it's
stability plus transformation and and I
would say that manifests itself you know
when you're there because that manifests
itself as meaningful that's actually the
the instinct of meaning which is an
instinct and perhaps the deepest
instinct is precisely the instinct that
tells you when where you are as
sufficiently stable but your
forming yourself at a sufficient rate to
keep up with everything that's changing
and you know that because if you're at
your job you might say to yourself well
my job is really secure but it's not
very challenging and you think well why
do you care about that it's very secure
and the answer to that is well if it's
not challenging it's it's deadening in a
sense right the spirit goes out of it if
it's not challenging you need to be
challenged and why is that well the
answer is well tomorrow is coming and
whoever you are now isn't enough for
tomorrow
and so today you also have to be
preparing for tomorrow and next week and
next year and if your job isn't
challenging then it isn't doing that for
you and you find it deadening not
meaningful and the reason for that is
that it violates your most essential
instinct and your most essential
instinct is the instinct for meaning and
it signifies that it actually signifies
that you have the balance between chaos
and order right deeply right which is
why it's the most fundamental of
instincts because chaos and order are
the most real of things all right so you
have the chaos that surrounds you and in
some some sense infinite in scope and
then you have the order that you produce
which is your mastery of it well let's
take order apart for a minute we want to
think about the structure of order and
I'm not saying that chaos is bad an
order is good I'm not saying that at all
that's not the right way to look at it
it's the balance piece it's the balance
between them that's of crucial
importance they just think they exist as
super ordinate categories whether you
like them or not is really not that
relevant they're there they're there the
fundamental constituent elements of
reality you might say well what's your
evidence for that and I can tell you one
piece of evidence which I won't go into
for very much time you have two
hemispheres and each in your brain the
brain is composed of two hemispheres
which implies something about the nature
of the world given that your brain is
hypothetically adapted to the structure
of the world it's not just your brain
because animal brains have the same
fundamental structure this bifurcated
structure and the bifurcation in
it's that there's two fundamental
realities because otherwise why would
you need a bifurcated structure or maybe
you need a triune brain or one that's
divided into four but that isn't what
you have you have one that's divided
into two and if your working definition
of reality is scientific biological
let's say then your definition of
reality is reality is that which shapes
life you can't actually do better than
that from a Darwinian perspective and if
the reality that shaped life produced a
bifurcated representational structure
then that implies that the proper way to
represent reality and perhaps that
reality itself is in fact bifurcated and
I believe it's bifurcated in the manner
I just described and the neurological
evidence for that is actually quite
overwhelming it's come from multiple
sources some of them Russians some of
them American that's where most of the
work has been done your left hemisphere
is specialized for operation in those
situations that you know and understand
and your right hemisphere is specialized
for operation in those situations that
you neither know nor understand and the
proper way to orient yourself in life is
to get the balance between those two
sets of operations correct and the way
that manifests itself in your subjective
experience is as meaningful engagement
and so that's not a bad first pass what
would you say justification for the view
that these two domains are the most real
domains
okay so order what is order well if you
just sit there and do nothing that will
be chaos why well because you'll you'll
suffer and die that's what will happen
so without action on your part
deterioration and death is a certainty
okay so you need to act well then we
built on an action-platformer
I mean we're the consequence of
three billion years of evolution for
action action movement forward in the
face of necessity is the prime dictum of
life that's a good way of thinking about
it
we're embodied action what do you have
to do when you act well at minimum you
have to do whatever keeps you able to
act
these are truisms right I mean you have
to have something to eat you have to
have some fresh water you need some
shelter right you need some
companionship you need a sexual partner
you need children you need play you need
to be touched there's there's a and I
mean I actually mean need by the way
people deprived of play go insane people
who aren't touched died these things are
necessary well assuming that survival
itself is necessary but we'll start with
that we'll start with the assumption
that just sitting there and suffering
and dying is not the right solution okay
so you have to act in the world
you have to act in the world that in a
manner that stops you from deteriorating
and dying at minimum and that means that
you have to address the problems that
are intrinsic to that destiny now you
have all sorts of systems that evolved
have evolved to help you do that
motivational systems we have to eat so
you get hungry you have to find water
and consume it so you get thirsty you
get lonely you get curious there's
there's there's specialized biological
systems that are very very old you get
aggressive you get afraid you you suffer
pain all those specialized systems for
all of those unidirectional systems of
orientation in the world and they help
you figure out what to do so when you're
hungry it's time to eat and when you're
thirsty it's it's time to drink and when
you're lonesome it's time to seek out
some companionship and you have
specialized systems that help you do
that but they're not enough because well
they're not very bright that's one way
of looking at it they're kind of uni
dimensional and you also have the
problem of organizing all of them it's
like well you have to eat now and you
have to drink now and you need a
companion
that's probably time to play and you
have to do something about shelter and
there isn't just you right now there's
you now
and tomorrow and next week in a year
from now and five years from now so you
have to plan across all those stretches
of time and there isn't just you now in
the future you there's you plus your
family and your community and so all of
that has to be taken into account while
you're plotting your movement forward
it's very very complicated you have all
these problems to solve simultaneously
and your motivational systems anger
hunger and so forth can help you solve
one of those problems now but not all of
them permanently that requires higher
cognitive function and that's part of
what drove the evolution of our complex
cognitive systems that's how do you
propagate the game across time in a
complex environment the left hemisphere
operates when where when what you're
doing works and so a lot of what you do
during your life is to keep your right
hemisphere off people don't like it
going on accidentally it's the home of
negative emotion it's the home of pain
and anxiety it's the thing that turns on
and freezes you and your tracks when
something that you deeply did not expect
happens and it prepares you to deal with
the onslaught of what you didn't expect
now it's not all bad news because to use
the right hemisphere in a judicious
manner is also something that adds
intrigue and interest and artistic
expression and all sorts of positive
things to your life
so because potential is not only
negative it's also positive it can be it
can be dealt with in ways that are
deeply enriching and meaningful order
okay so you have to do something
otherwise the consequences are dire to
do something you have to value something
it's it's it's a definitional issue
because to do something is to act out
the proposition that the thing you're
doing the thing you're aiming at let's
say is preferable to the thing you have
and preferable means you'll do it so
those things are tied together so
tightly you can't disentangle them if
you say I'm aiming at X but I don't
value it then there's something wrong
with the way that you're conceptualizing
the statement because to aim at
something
and to work to bring it into existence
is the same as valuing it and if you say
well I don't value it then something's
out of kilter either you're acting out a
falsehood or you don't know what you're
talking about it's one of those two
things and you meet people like that or
deeply confused they're their action
patterns and their verbal
self-representation don't mesh but that
doesn't mean that they're critics of
value it just means that they're deeply
confused so you have to act or you
suffer in order to act you have to have
a value structure because to act you
have to value one thing more than
another which means that you have to
inhabit a structure of value you have to
okay so you need a structure value
because it's the antidote to catastrophe
now if you act out a structure of value
socially which you will because your
social you're not gonna pursue your aims
in isolation because you're not you're
not a solitary animal you're a social
animal you're a tribal animal deeply
tribal we live in groups we live in
families we live in communities we live
in large societies we're social at every
level of analysis and we've been social
for as long as we've been primates so
maybe that's that's at least six million
years and it might be more like 60
million years it's really a long time so
it's not an arbitrary social
construction it's far far deeper than
that now what happens when you act out a
structure of value in a social
environment you produce a hierarchy
inevitably well let's think it through
why well let's say that you say that one
thing is more worth doing than another
whatever happens to be and then you tell
a bunch of people about what you're
doing and they decide that they're gonna
come along and help you do this thing
that's valuable because they also think
it's valuable and maybe you get 20
people together to do this thing
whatever it happens to be and the first
thing you discover is that some of the
people are way better at doing whatever
it is
they're doing than other people so and
that and who knows why that is because
it depends on what you chose to do you
know if you chose a then it would be a
different group of people who were good
at it than if you chose B because people
differ in their abilities but one thing
you will not escape from if you make an
organization to do something valuable is
the brute fact that it will be a
minority of the people who are good at
doing it and there's actually a law it's
called prices law and it's a real law it
even governs the size of cities and the
mass of stars and the heights of plants
in the jungle
it just doesn't govern human
interactions and prices law says that
the square root of the number of people
engaged in the enterprise will do half
the work so if you have ten people doing
something three of them will do half the
work but if you have a hundred people
doing something then ten of them will do
half the work and if you have 10,000
people doing something then a hundred of
them will do half the work and then you
know how wealth distributes itself such
that a minority of people have most of
the money 1285 richest people in the
world have as much money as the bottom
two and a half billion it's something
like that and everybody goes oh my god
the 1% it's like well first of all
you're all the 1% so get over yourself
because you're you know Western European
roughly speaking and by world current
world standards and certainly by
historical standards you're all well
ensconced in the 1% so if that's a
problem well it's a problem for all of
you and some of you might be you know
richer than that but that doesn't mean
all of you aren't in the same boat
fundamentally the fact that wealth
aggregates in the hands of a small
number of people is part of the general
expression of prices law there's nothing
special about the distribution of money
you see the same thing in every creative
domain I mean how many of you have have
recorded a gold record how many looks
like zero up there's one one person okay
there's 850 people in here so there's
one in a thousand so that's
1/10 of 1% something like that how many
of you have written a piano concerto
how about painted a painting that's
hanging in a national museum oh look
it's none of you again right well and
how many of you have been a member of a
professional sports team okay look up 1
1 so that's one in a thousand well you
get the point here well there was a
couple there is okay so looks like it's
easier to be a member of a professional
sports team or my or my audience is set
is biased the samples biased but but it
is the case if you look at high levels
of creative achievement of the sword
I've just described they they
characterized a staggering minority of
people and so the rule is is that you
produce a value system which you better
produce because otherwise you suffer and
die and it isn't only that only that
it's like look here's something else you
all know as far as I can tell we start
with the idea that there's an intrinsic
chaotic element to life and that
includes the inevitability of suffering
and malevolence betrayal at the hands of
yourself and other people so that's the
baseline and that's intolerable in many
ways because life is in many ways
intolerable and the question is well
what do you do in the face of something
that's intolerable and the answer is
well you try to find something that
justifies it right you want to have
something that gets you the hell out of
bed in the morning and not just any old
morning but a morning when your father
has Alzheimer's disease and your
daughter has an incurable illness
because you need something to get out of
bed for in those mornings - and that
better be the purpose that you found in
life and if the purpose is going to be
such that it gets you out of bed in
those mornings it better be a pretty
damn noble purpose because otherwise why
would you bother and so not only do you
need a value structure you need one
that's of sufficient tension let's say
or sufficient value or sufficient
nobility so that it's worth suffering
for because you're going to suffer and
you better have something that makes the
suffering justifiable and so not only do
you need the value
structure so that you don't just
deteriorate and die you need the value
structure so that when the flood comes
in your life as it certainly will that
you have built a vessel that will
sustain you through the catastrophe and
that's not this pursuit of happiness
it's not even the pursuit of security
it's none of that
it's your the orientation that you've
managed to produce in your own life
towards a higher good that's so high
that it's worth bearing the burden of
being to produce you implement that in
the world you produce a hierarchy now
you might say well and then you have the
problem of hierarchy and the problem of
hierarchy is a very few people are going
to be very good at whatever that
hierarchy does and then you have the
second problem with hierarchy which is
the problem I just laid out when I asked
you about your spectacular levels of
attainment and found out that they were
very it was very unlikely I'm not saying
that you haven't attained worthwhile
things that's not my point my point is
is that very high levels of attainment
are extraordinarily rare and that's an
inevitability as soon as you decide that
something's worth doing to
inevitabilities people stack up at the
top minority of people stack up at the
top and take most of the proceeds
whatever they happen to be or deserve
them or earn them whatever however I
don't care how you conceptualize it and
almost everybody else stacks up at the
bottom and so the problem with
hierarchies is that even though they're
necessary they tend to produce a
situation where most people stack up at
the bottom and so that's the next thing
that we have to contend with you can't
get rid of the hierarchies because if
you get rid of the hierarchies there's
no value structure and if there's no
value structure not only do you
deteriorate and die you want to
deteriorate and die and that's not a
good solution but if you do generate a
hierarchy then you have the problem of
the hierarchy and the problem of the
hierarchy is that it will dis possess
most people now to the degree that the
post modernists have something to say
that's what they say is hierarchies dis
possess okay and then we can look at
that clearly and carefully and we can
say that doesn't mean a
that hierarchies themselves are corrupt
or that we can dispense with them but it
also doesn't mean that we have no moral
obligation to the dispossessed and we
say well how do we deal with that
politically conceptually and the way we
deal with that at least in part is to
produce a political spectrum that ranges
from left to right that deals with
hierarchy and the problems that
hierarchies cause so one of the things
that you can reliably assume about
someone who's on the right is that they
will be patriotically in favor of the
current hierarchy or even more
abstractly they're in favor of the idea
of hierarchy itself and you say well
more power to the people on the right
because you need hierarchies so they
should support them but then you have to
take the people on the left you say yeah
but what about the people who are
dispossessed by the hierarchy and what
you have to say to them is yeah we
actually have to do something about that
and you think well how do we do
something about that and the answer is
we don't actually know because there's
no permanent solution to the problem of
dispossession by the hierarchy we don't
know how to fix it say well we could
flatten the hierarchies it's like not
without disrupting the value structure
that's a price you don't want to pay
well we could take from the top and put
it at the bottom it's like yes
hypothetically we could but it turns out
that when you try that in practice it's
very very easy to rapidly go too far and
then what you end up with naught is less
dispossessed you end up with no one who
has anything and that's not a good
solution to the problem of scarcity
right to make everyone equally dead or
equally starving which is essentially
what the Communist States did across the
entirety of the twentieth century is not
the proper way to address the problem of
hierarchy now it has to be addressed
even if you're on the right because
here's one thing that happens
hierarchies tend to ossify you know
because what happens is that the people
at the top maybe they got there by
merit but it's easy for them to
gerrymander the system so they can stay
there without merit or perhaps their
children can stay there without merit or
they can or the hierarchy becomes
corrupt so that people who only use
tyranny and power can climb it and so
you don't have a hierarchy of competence
and value anymore you have a hierarchy
of brute power which looks like a
tyranny so there's all sorts of ways
that hierarchies can deteriorate and we
have to be awake to ensure that that
doesn't occur also if the hierarchy gets
so steep that everybody stacks up at
zero and no one can climb it which is
basically the definition of a
malfunctioning tyranny than all the
people at the bottom rightly think well
why don't we just destroy the game
because we're already at zero so what
the hell do we have to lose and so one
of the things that you want to do if
you're a sensible conservative is make
sure that the hierarchy maintains its
rooting incompetence that it's
transparent and that it's Klima Bowl
because otherwise it will ossify and
steepen and then it will destroy itself
and if you're a conservative and you
value stability and the hierarchy then
you don't want to set up a situation
where the most likely outcome is that
the hierarchy destroys itself so so we
can be intelligent about this we could
say look don't be thinking you can get
rid of hierarchies they've been around
this is why I wrote chapter one I talked
about lobsters the reason I talked about
them is because not only is the
hierarchical structure itself as a
permanent feature of existence at least
a third of a billion years old which by
the way means that you cannot attribute
it to capitalism the free market or the
corrupt patriarchal West unless you're
willing to make the case that all three
of those elements contributed to the
existence of dominance hierarchies among
crustaceans which seems highly unlikely
so and and this is actually something
that's that it's you could think about
it as an idea that's actually directed
towards the productive left if you want
to help the dispossessed don't blame the
existence of hierarchies on
capitalism because it's wrong it's wrong
that the problem is way deeper than that
and here's something else that's very
interesting about capitalism a couple of
things you might consider you know we
have become spectacularly wealthy since
1895 right first in the West Iceland is
a classic example I mean you guys are so
much more wealthy than you were a
hundred years ago that it's absolutely
impossible to believe and so that's
first happened in the West exponential
economic growth starting in about 1895
there's a long tail I mean people were
improving before that but it really
kicked in around 1895 and first happened
in the West and now it's happening
everywhere in the world I don't know if
you know this but you know the UN set a
goal in 2000 to have the level of
absolute poverty in the world by 2015
which is the fastest rate of economic
growth ever recorded we attained it in
2012 three years ahead of the most
optimistic projections right and so
people are being lifted out of poverty
at a rate that has never been seen in
the history of the world hooked to the
power grids provided with cell phones
provided with free with access to fresh
water provided with access to
medications that decrease child
mortality like if you look at the
statistics there are so many things
getting better so fast you cannot even
believe it and that's and here's that's
a consequence as far as as far as the
data indicate of the operation of the
free market system which does produce
inequality that's the thing but as far
as I can tell the only system that has
ever produced wealth and as law or has
every system produces inequality but the
only system we know of that produces
produces wealth and inequality is the
free market so here's a question for
everyone left and right how many units
of inequality will you tolerate to
produce one unit of wealth and if the
answer is zero then you've gone too far
you're outside the appropriate political
debate that's the wrong answer and if
you try to impose that all there will be
as mayhem because the price we pay for
wealth is inequality now that doesn't
mean
that you can let inequality run to its
ultimate extreme because then you run
into the other problem which is the
monopoly problem you've all played
Monopoly I presume what happens in every
Monopoly game if you play it out
everyone stacks out at zero up at zero
except one person now if you play it 50
times you'll find that it's hardly ever
the same person because it's basically a
game of chance and there's a fair bit of
chance by the way operating in the
distribution of money in the world it's
not all chance but there's a fair bit of
chance but the logical conclusion to a
hierarchy that can play itself out
totally is that one person has
everything and everyone else has nothing
obviously that's not a useful outcome so
so you know and the way there are ways
that we fix that in our society we have
progressive tax policies and you can
argue about their utility but that's one
way of rectifying it potentially another
way of rectifying is that we don't have
one game right in a pluralistic society
we have many many games that people can
play and so if you can't be a successful
lawyer then maybe you could be a
successful plumber and if you can't be a
successful plumber maybe you can run a
small restaurant or you know there's a
diversity of games and so that's a good
way of allowing of increasing the
robustness of the system so that you
don't get hierarchies that are so steep
that they collapse in and I'm in an you
know in upon themselves and so those are
sophisticated approaches and perhaps
your other approaches too but it's an
intractable problem it says in the new
testament it's one of the things you'd
swear would be edited out because it's
such a harsh statement the poor will be
with us always well what's that in
reference to it's also in reference to
the Matthieu principle which is another
New Testament statement and happens to
be an economic axiom to those who have
everything more will be given from those
who have nothing everything will be
taken that's the structure of the world
and you can't lay it at the feet of the
West it's the structure of the world now
that means we have to contend with it
and it's not an easy thing to contend
with and part of the reason that we have
a continual political dialogue and that
we need to have a continual political
dialogue is to make sure that our
hierarchies exist and remain in
tact but don't become so steep and
corrupt that they destroy themselves and
you need a left and a right for that and
if and buts that means the left half it
has to admit that hierarchies are not
only necessary but valuable and the
right has to admit that despite their
necessity in value they tend to stack
people up at the bottom and that
actually constitutes a continual problem
you see that in you see that in the Old
Testament because one of the things that
happens in the Old Testament is Israel
struggles up to state and Empire status
six times it struggles out of the chaos
up to Empire status and then it gets
corrupt it loses the way it isn't
balancing things between chaos and order
properly the kings get arrogant is so to
the people and they forget their
relationship with God that's another way
of thinking about it and then a prophet
comes up and says you aren't paying
enough attention to the widows and the
orphans you better look out because that
displeases God and the Israelites who
are stiff-necked and arrogant think
what's God going to do to us which is
not a very wise way of thinking and so
they don't take the steps necessary to
rectify their deviation from the proper
path and they get absolutely flattened
and the consequences of that lasts for
generations like seven generations and
then they struggle their way up to
something approximating Empire status
again and exactly the same thing happens
they forget and they collapse there's
six stories like that in the Old
Testament it's all documented by a man
named Northrop Frye who is a Canadian
literary critic who wrote a couple of
books on the Bible one called the Great
Code and the other called words with
power which I I would highly recommend
it's an analysis of the Bible as
literature brilliant for those of you
who might be interested in Union
thinking Frye's thinking is a nice
adjunct so all right so so that's the
nature of the world order chaos and
order and your goal is to keep those the
relationship between those two things
optimized and you do that by doing
what's meaningful not what's expedient
that's rule 6
and you ensure that you have the world
construed properly by following rule
number eight which is tell the truth or
at least don't lie you don't want to
pathologies the instinct that Orient's
you in the world and you will
pathologize it by engaging in habitual
deceit and the reason you do that is
when you practice something you build
structures that specialize in that and
then they run automatically so if you're
living a lie which is a very common
thing for people to do then you're
building neurological mechanisms that
view the world through that lie and once
they're built there you and good luck
unbuilding them it's very very difficult
that's in part what happens to people
who are addicted by the way they build
mechanisms of search neurological
structures that are focused on the drug
and those systems are alive and all they
want is the drug and they're they're not
it's not psychological exactly
it's psychophysiological don't build
structures of cognition predicated on
deception because you will pay for it
and so if you're gonna guide your life
with the orientation of the instinctive
meaning then you have to be very careful
with what you say and write and think
because every time you say or write or
think something you build a little
neurological structure that's
specialized for that and it participates
in this parsing of the world so alright
chaos and order then you can say the
order orders a hierarchy okay so here's
the next question next to questions is
order a hierarchy and then a subsidiary
question would be if order is a
hierarchy what's well either what is at
the top of the hierarchy or what should
be at the top of the hierarchy said
hierarchy is a structure of value so
that's the question is what should be of
all commit value okay so now we're gonna
take that apart a little bit the first
thing I would say is order is not a
hierarchy order is a set of hierarchies
that's a different thing so I'll tell
you how to think about that I think so
imagine you have a child and they're
playing soccer and your child's a pretty
good soccer player no I'll tell you a
different story
this actually happened so I'm gonna tell
you a story about hockey and I'm since
I'm Canadian what the hell I might as
well tell you a story about hockey um my
son played hockey he still plays hockey
he's a pretty good hockey player and my
wife and I used to go watch him play
hockey
there was an arena just down the street
from us and there was a nice
neighborhood League there and so they'd
sort the kids into teams and then they'd
let them play a few demo games and if
any team was getting stomped flat or any
other team was winning too much then
they'd rebalanced the team so that they
were approximately equal in skill so
that was the sorting of the teams so and
then they then they were on their teams
and then they play you know 15 games
during the regular season they'd have a
little tournament to see who won and it
was really good it was good friendly
League and so my son's team was in I
think it was the championship game if I
remember correctly and there's one kid
on his team who was the best player on
the team but by quite a margin you know
he was very fast on his feet
he could he could skate rings around a
lot of the kids he was good at stick
handling he was a good hockey player but
he had some problems this kid one
problem was he wouldn't pass the puck
now you think well why the hell should
you pass the puck if you had the best
hockey player which is pretty much what
he thought and the answer is well you're
part of a team right you want to be the
best person on the team fair enough and
you want to win the hockey game but you
also want to what make your team mates
better players how's that maybe you even
want to make the people on other teams
better players I mean I know that's
going a little bit too far but you
certainly want to make your teammates
better players and you might think well
why would you do that because if they're
better then maybe you won't be the best
well that's a boneheaded way of looking
at the world because first of all if you
amp up the competition around you maybe
that'll motivate you to be even better
and it's a hell of a way to win by
making everyone else lose that's not
much of a victory and so if you have any
sense you pass the damn puck even if
you're the better player especially you
especially do that let's say you've got
it comfortable two goal lead well then
maybe you can risk taking the time away
from that specific game to build up the
confident confidence and ability of your
teammates and then maybe everybody
thinks that you're a bit of a leader and
they make you team captain not even so
much because you're the best hockey
player but because well because why
that's the question okay so we're
watching the game and it's pretty
exciting and it's real close game and
it's like 3 2 3 and it's a minute left
and the other team zips down the nice
and scores a really brilliant goal and
so my son's team loses except that they
were in the championship and it was a
really good game so you know whether or
not they lost is not all that obvious
they lost that game but you know there's
a broader context to take into
consideration ok so this kid the this
the star goes
off the ice and he takes his hockey
stick and he smashes it on to the cement
and he's all angry because as far as he
was concerned he was robbed and maybe
that's because of his useless teammates
who he didn't really spend any time
helping by the way and maybe it's
because the referees were unfair and who
the hell knows why but it wasn't fair
and his idiot farther rushes over to him
and consoles him in on his loss and
supports him in his notion that he was
robbed and I thought you unspeakable son
of a because he was an arrogant
narcissist and it was way more important
to him that he had a son who was a star
than that he had a son who is a good
person and that's absolutely inexcusable
he made the wrong choice he sacrificed
his son's soul in part to help him save
face for a hockey game that's not
acceptable
ok so here's what you tell your children
it doesn't matter whether you win or
lose it matters how you play the game
and so that's what the father should
have told the son and he should have
meant it and even better he should have
known what it meant but who knows what
that means because you tell your
children that and maybe they're not so
happy because they lost a game and they
look at you like you're an alien and
they think well what the hell do you
mean by that because obviously it
matters whether you win and it does
matter whether you win so what is it
that you mean when you say that and your
kid asks well what do you mean by that
and you go well I don't know what it
means but it's a good rule so what do
you mean by that here's what you mean
and it relates to rule 5 which is don't
make your don't let your children do
anything that makes you dislike them
because other people will dislike them
then and you don't want other people to
dislike your children unless you want
your children to inhabit a world where
everyone dislikes them and maybe you do
you don't like your children and maybe
you don't like your children because you
let them behave in ways that makes you
not like them and so the way you take
revenge is by not correcting them so
that other people will punish them
because you don't have the courage to
discipline them and if you think that
people don't play that game then you
don't know much about people because
they play that game all the time all
right so it matters how you play the
game it doesn't matter whether you win
or lose let's take that apart well so
the first thing is and this goes back to
the idea the hierarchy is order a
hierarchy and the answer is no it's a
set of all hierarchies or you could say
it's the it's the set of all possible
hierarchies because you know in a
society at a given time there's
hierarchies that function but that
transforms and then there's new
hierarchies that function the the
specifics of the hierarchies change but
the fact of the hierarchies remains and
so you can imagine a hierarchy as a meta
structure that consists of a multitude
of possible hierarchies and that's going
to change as life continues and so what
you want for your children is not to be
the master of a hierarchy you want for
your children to be the master of the
set of all possible hierarchies because
then no matter how things change they're
ready say well how is it that you get
ready for things to change and the
answer is play so that people will
invite you to play right and there's a
rule for for children for raising
children and it really it's a rule one
of the things you can do with your
children this is something good for men
because men are more likely to do this
than women although women can do it too
but men are more likely to do it it's
really good for children to engage in
rough-and-tumble play play fighting
first of all if you have children and
you've played with them physically you
know that they absolutely love it they
will rough-and-tumble play with you
until you are completely exhausted and
they're not even vaguely ready to quit
they have an inexhaustible hunger for it
and they like it they like to be pushed
to the edge so I knew this when I was a
new father
because I read work by a man named yak
panksepp who was a genius an effective
neuroscientist one of the world's great
neuroscientists perhaps the world's
greatest neuroscientist although there's
four or five people that might compete
with him he wrote a book called
affective neuroscience emotional
neuroscience which is a work of real
genius he discovered the play circuit in
mammals because there's a separate play
circuit in mammals a specialized circuit
and he did a lot of work on rats and
showing that in order for a rat to
become socialized because rats are
highly social they had to engage in
iterative bouts of rough-and-tumble play
and here's a cool thing it's a
ridiculously cool thing so and this has
to do in some sense with the postmodern
critique of the patriarchal tyranny so
if you take to juvenile rats
males and you imagine you give them an
opportunity to play so you throw two of
them into a little play arena and you
let the wrestle okay the next time that
you bring them to the same place you can
measure how much work they'll do to open
the door to the arena how many times
they'll push a button say to open the
door or haw-haw-haw hard they'll pull if
you tie a strength spring to their tail
and so you can get an estimate of their
motivation because the more motivated
they are to play the harder they'll work
and rats will work really hard to play
so you know that they want to play I
mean assuming that you're willing to
accept the fact that if you work for
something you want it it's like an
operational definition so rats will work
to play now if you let the rats out in
the play arena and one rat is ten
percent bigger than the other then that
rat will win you might say well what
does winning mean and rats wrestle like
people wrestle
they even pin each other and they
manifest play behavior to begin with
like dogs playing in a park you know how
a dog looks when it wants to play it
sort of hunkers down a little bit looks
up at you like expectance expectantly
kind of move back and forth which is
like okay human I'm ready to play and if
you have any sense and you know how to
play then you look at the dog and you
sort of go like this and the dog goes
like this
and you cuff the dog not too hard and
the dog bites you
not too hard and then you can play and
you're both happy with that and kids can
do that with dogs because kids
understand dogs and dogs and kids know
how to play if if your dog can't play
then you should not own a dog because
you're not smart enough to own a dog
so it's true and if you have a dog that
can't play then don't have a kid right
it's true the stupidest dog I ever saw
was owned by a psychologist that was
really embarrassing so okay so you put
the rat two rats together and there's
the 10% bigger rod and there's the 10%
smaller rat and the 10% bigger rat
stomps the small rat and pins him so he
wins and so now you're a postmodernist
doing the experiment and you say
powerful tyrannical rat dominates
hierarchy really really that's what you
conclude end of experiment and you're
and it looks correct because powerful
dominant rat dominated and one it's like
okay except for one thing rats live with
rats they don't wander they're not
psychopathic individuals wandering from
isolated community to isolated community
they know all the other rats and that
means they have to keep playing with
them and the rules for playing with
someone thirty times are not the same as
the rules for playing with someone once
so panksepp had the rats play repeatedly
and what he observed was okay now the
next time you put those rats together
the situation is a little different
the little rat comes bouncing out and
does the playful dog thing too the big
rat so now the rule is you're the little
rat you lost you have to be the creature
that invites to play that's now your
status so you bounce around and you know
the big rats all cool and he's smoking a
cigarette and doesn't want to doesn't
want to play but he'll flick it away at
some point and think all right what the
hell you know and so then he gets in it
and so he can stomp the little rat again
because he's a bigger rat
if the big rat doesn't let the little
rat win 30% of the time across repeated
play boats then the little rat won't ask
him to play anymore you think well if
you think about you don't think so what
you don't think why did yo King Sepp
waste his time studying playing rats you
think oh my god that's an absolute
miracle because it shows you that
there's an ethic of fair play that
emerges as a consequence of repeated
bouts of play even among rats it's so
basic it isn't even human that ethic the
ethic of fair play is deeper than human
it's real and it's the ethic that
governs iterated interactions and it's
not just in rats that we've seen this so
you know chimpanzees are pretty damn
brutal they're way more brutal than you
think and they're really really strong
maybe six times as strong as an adult
male now there's the estimates vary but
they're plenty strong enough to tear you
to bits and that happens now and then
people have chimps for pets and they
become adults and it's like don't mess
with the chimp because it'll tear you to
pieces and so and chimps are brutal and
this is interesting because they're our
closest relatives and so Jane Goodall
discovered in the 1970s that rats our
tribe or chimps are tribal they live in
tribal groups like we do and they have a
territory that's the known territory and
there's a perimeter that's the unknown
that's chaos and other chimpanzees
inhabit the chaos foreign chimpanzees
and the juvenile chimps patrol the
perimeters in groups of four or five and
if they spy us a foreign chimp or two of
them if they outnumber them because they
can't count but they have a sense of
quantity if five chimps come across to
foreign chimps they will tear them to
bits and I actually mean that literally
that's what they do and chimps also hunt
they hunt colobus monkeys and they weigh
about 40 pounds and they're quite
carnivorous and they will eat them alive
well they're screaming so there isn't a
lot of empathy regulating chimp
aggression which is something to think
about when you think about human beings
because it's not obvious what regulates
our aggression and you might think well
it's your conscience and like yeah
maybe it's your conscience and maybe
it's something else if you read the book
of you read The Rape of Nanking for
example and you'll start wondering very
very rapidly about whether people have
any conscience at all so that's a story
of absolutely atrocious Japanese
behavior in China at at the beginning of
World War two it's a horrifying book so
read it with caution but it's very
instructive so anyways the chimps the
chimps are very brutal creatures and so
you might think well let's look at a
chimp hierarchy because chimps have
dominance hierarchies and they're
basically male-dominated although there
are lots of powerful female chimps say
ok who becomes the dominant chimp and
the answer might be and this would be
the postmodern answer the most powerful
tyrannical brutal chimp rules because
its power that moves you up the
hierarchy it's like that happens
sometimes among chimps but you know what
happens to tyrant chimps they have an
off day and to subordinate chimps each
3/4 the size gang up to make a one and a
half super chimp and then they tear him
to pieces right so here's the rule if
you're a chimp tyrants meet bloody ends
so how do you conduct yourself as a
chimp if you want to be at the top of
the hierarchy and have preferential
access to the things that being at the
top of the hierarchy would give you an
answer is engage in mutually reciprocal
interactions with your peers the chimps
that rise to the top that stay there
stabili and also have the most stable
functioning troops by the way are the
ones that have friends that are
long-term and permanent and engage in
reciprocal interactions not only with
their friends but also with the females
and the infants and so even among chimps
patriarchal tyranny a is not the norm
and B is not the proper mode of
approaching the situation and so that
speaks to a broader ethic the same kind
of ethic that is spoken to with regards
to the rat studies of play behavior and
you can see this sort of thing
throughout the animal kingdom there's a
there's a pattern of reciprocal
interaction that seems to stabilize
social animals that isn't predicated on
brute force now maybe the simpler the
animal the more its predicated on brute
force but we are by no means simple
animals and the idea that our
hierarchies are fundamentally tyrannical
the patriarchy which is a word that
nobody who thinks carefully should ever
use casually that term is predicated on
the idea that hey that our hierarchies
are tyrannical which they aren't
although they can become that way and be
that the most reliable means to
attaining status within a hierarchy is
through the expression of power and both
of those things are wrong they're wrong
and nonetheless that's the primary
theory of the social sciences and the
humanities enough of that we've we have
enough data to indicate that none of
that's sufficiently sophisticated to
constitute a reasonable explanation of
the world so we should dispense with it
as fast as possible all it's doing is
dividing us into tribes and it's not
solving the problems that it's
hypothetically intended to solve so ok
so now back to the question so there
isn't a hierarchy there's a set of
hierarchies and it's like the set of
games so here's what you're telling your
child when you say doesn't matter
whether you win or lose it matters how
you play the game what you're telling
them is life is not a game it's not even
a sequence of the same games it's
multiple sequences of different games
and if you want to be a successful
player in the set of multiple sequence
of different games then you have to
adopt a higher order ethic and you don't
subordinate that ethic to victory in any
one game ever so you put the manner in
which you play above your victory in in
each instance and the reason that that
produces
the best possible outcome for you is
that you get invited to play the largest
number of games and so let's go back to
rule 5 don't let your children do
anything that makes you dislike them
okay so let's say you like your children
let's say you love your children and you
want the best for them you detach
yourself a little bit you think well I'm
not gonna be around forever and they're
going to deal with a lot of different
people single people like individuals
groups of people children and adults and
what they have to be prepared for is to
interact with that set of people in the
best possible manner because and so what
do you want well let's say your child's
too and it's still pretty egocentric
because children shoot two-year-olds are
quite egocentric they can't share yet
they don't really learn how to share in
any technical sense till they're about
three it's hard for them to learn to
share between two and four they learn to
share and to play and the way they learn
is by at least in part by engaging in
reciprocal interactions with their
parents now what is it that it what is
it that's your job when you're
socializing a child who's 2 to 4 you
have to do it between the ages of 2 & 4
by the way because if you don't manage
it by the time they're 4 then you might
as well give up because it isn't going
to happen and the literature on
antisocial behavior in children is
crystal clear on this point if your
child's antisocial at 4 you've failed
and there isn't anything that can be
done about it
it's a dismal literature and believe me
psychologists and sociologists and
anthropologists and criminologists have
tried for like six decades to figure out
how to remediate antisocial behavior in
older children and adolescents and they
haven't managed it so so between 2 & 4
is crucial you want to help your child
become the sort of person that other
children want to play with and the
reason you want to do that is because
from 4 onward other children are the
primary agents of socialization and so
if your children are accepted by other
children
then they're on their way because other
children will socialize them doesn't
mean you're not important as a parent
but it means they find their peers who
are at the same developmental level as
them and they start to reciprocally
socialize one another and they do that
through play and so if you've prepared
your child to be a great play companion
then you can just stand back and let it
happen and you have to be around when
something breaks down when the system
doesn't work properly you have to be
there as a resource but basically you
can sort of push them out onto the
playground and say you know you know
what to do go play and play is of
absolutely crucial importance as
documented by people like Jean Piaget so
you're trying to make your child
maximally attractive as a play partner
and the ethic there is well the world is
made out of a sequence of hierarchies
that transform and so you want your
child to be the sort of person who's
invited to participate in whatever
hierarchy organizes itself and how and
what should a child be like to do that
well they have to be reciprocal take
turns right you don't always get to pick
the game you have to find out what other
people want to do they have to want to
play - like there's all these
sophisticated ethical rules that go
around play and you know if you're
playing with some of you have played
with kids that aren't fun to play with
well what are they like if something
doesn't go their way what happens they
have an emotional outburst so they
revert to the behavior of a ill-prepared
two-year-old they have a temper tantrum
they burst into tears they thrash around
on the floor it's not fun because when
you play if you don't lose sometimes
then no one else ever wins so who the
hell is gonna play with someone like
that
a downtrodden victim that's all it's not
no kid with any sense is gonna put up
with that all they didn't this is
exactly what kids are like if they find
out that their potential play partner is
a whiny two-year-old even though
therefore they just stop playing and
they go find another kid that's exactly
what happens and so if you want that for
your kid then make sure that their whiny
and
better every time they lose a good way
to do that is to never let them lose it
anything so they don't get any practice
well I don't want my kid to lose it's
like wrong you don't want to you don't
want your kid to lose in an
unsophisticated manner that's not the
same thing at all if you think the way
you accomplish that is by never having
your kid lose then well then well then
we're back to the you shouldn't even own
a dog problem all right so then you
might take apart what does it mean to be
a desirable play partner assuming you're
gonna play reciprocal repeated games
across all sorts of different contexts
well there's a there's a whole ethic
that emerges from that see Nietzsche
back in the late 1800s he was the first
person to kind of caught on to this sort
of thing because until then people
tended to think of morality as something
that was invented rationally and then
imposed from the top down but Nietzsche
being a very intelligent observer noted
that well that wasn't really the case
there was a ethic already built into
human interactions that we all acted out
but that we didn't really understand
very well so here's a way to think about
that so imagine you're watching a wolf
pack and wolves compete for dominance
and so the way they do that is they
basically have a play fight about it now
it's this fairly serious play fight and
so two wolves that are engaged in a
dominus dispute will sort of sand
sideways to each other you know how cats
do that you ever watched two cats fight
cats stand sideways think well why does
a cat stand sideways when it's fighting
it's because a sideways cat is a bigger
cat than a head-on cat so the cats
trying to intimidate the other cat so it
stands sideways then it puffs itself up
including its tail and the reason it
does that is so that it looks bigger
because one cat isn't there cats don't
want to fight they want to threaten
until one cat backs down and so they
puff themselves up and they make
horrible noises and they face off
against each other but they don't want
to fight because the two cats that are
fighting might damage
each other then a third cat comes in and
like winds it's a stupid strategy so
it's it is so most animals don't like to
fight because they might damage
themselves and then another interloper
will just win it's a stupid strategy and
human beings are quite a bit like that
we do a lot of posturing and defensive
display and aggressive display and all
that but we don't fight very often for
that for the same reasons and it's only
when those other mechanisms break down
that we actually fight so what happens
in a wolf dispute is this the Wolves
square off and they amp up the threats
in the hope that one of the wolves will
back to hell down because what will
happen is the wolf will chicken out one
of them and then when it does it rolls
over and shows its neck why well because
when wolves hunt they go for the neck
generally like wolves are quite cruel
creatures in some sense and they'll
actually eat moose standing up but
generally speaking if they can manage it
they go through for the throat and
they'll bring the animal down and so
what the wolf is basically saying is
well you scared me half to death I'm a
useful Moo I'm a useless moose you might
as well tear out my neck and the other
wolf says yeah you're pretty detestable
and you're kind of like a moose but I
might need you to hunt tomorrow so I
know I could tear out your neck but I
won't
and then the defeated wolf stands up and
he's not very happy and he's kind of a
low status wolf but at least he's still
got his neck and the victor wolf gets to
be high status wolf and he gets to go
hunting with his partner the next day
and so you might think well wolves have
a complex procedural morality and the
morality is don't tear the neck out of
your out of the purr of out of the
creature you defeat that's wrong and
then you might say well that's the rule
that wolves follow but that's wrong
because wolves don't follow rules
because wolves don't have rules because
they don't have language and they don't
think not like us they act like they
have rules they act so that if you watch
them act you could label
what they're doing with the rule that's
how we got our rules that's how we got
our rules we acted out an ethic and then
we watched and then we coated it in
stories that's what our religious
stories are they're the consequence of
us watching what it is that we do when
we act ethically and then transforming
that into a story and everyone's intent
on that story it's absolutely intent on
the story of good versus evil let's say
because that's the fundamental story and
why do you want to watch that story
because you want to know how to be the
victor in the set of all possible games
and that's what that story's about and
that's what movies are about and that's
what books are about and that's what
religious narratives are about that's
what everything that grips us at a
literary level is about and the reason
that it grips us is because that's what
the world is made of and that's what we
need to know so then you might think so
here's something to think about
I'll give you a symbolic representation
of this okay so there's this idea in
Christianity and I'm not talking about
this from a religious perspective okay
I'm talking about this from an
anthropological perspective or a
biological perspective or a that'll do
an anthropological or a viola or
psychological perspective so there's
this idea in Christianity that Christ is
whatever Christ is is the king of kings
okay so I'm gonna take that apart so
imagine that you have a hierarchy
whatever it is and there's someone at
the top of it and so that's person has
the attributes necessary to be at the
top of that hierarchy maybe it's a
hockey team and you go home and you tell
a story about how the best hockey player
on your team played while they were
being the best hockey player it's a
little hero narrative it's a little
fragment of a hero narrative and maybe
it's hockey soccer plumbing law business
art there's all these hierarchies and
then there's the thing that's at the top
of all of them and the thing that's all
that at the top of all of them has
something in common that's whatever it
is that's in common across all the
things that are at the top
so imagine this okay so you could think
about this
imagine that you're a novelist and you
want to distill some characters and you
want a good evil character because what
the hell good is your book without a
good evil character and you want a good
good character because the same problem
place you don't want to just tell a
story about some guy's day right you
don't want to say well John woke up at 6
and then he smacked his lips four times
and blinked 20 times and then he swung
his feet over across the bed and walked
into the bathroom because who cares
about any of that you don't need to know
that because you know how to move your
mouth and COFF and walk to the bathroom
it's not helpful you want a distillation
you want the novelist who have watched a
bunch of people and abstracted out
someone who's good in a way that's good
across a bunch of people and you want
them to have abstracted out someone
who's evil that's abstract across a
bunch of evil characters so you see that
in Hamlet for example you see that
Dostoyevsky where the where the
characters are bigger than life and you
want them bigger than life because you
want it distilled so that you can learn
from it and what you're learning is that
ethic
okay so then imagine that you have a
hundred of hierarchies just mundane
hierarchies then you take the people at
the top of all those hierarchies say
that you grouped them into groups of ten
okay so you take ten admirable people
and then you say well we're gonna
average across them and we're gonna come
out with the most out with a composite
admirable person made out of those ten
you have a hundred to begin with so you
let's say you have a thousand to begin
with you distill them to a hundred
admirable people then you take that
hundred admirable people and you distill
them into ten and then you take those
ten admirable people and you distill
them into one and what that one is is
what's admirable across the entire set
of admirable people that's a divine
figure in a mythological story that's
what it is and so the Christian idea is
Christ is the king of kings and that's
what it means you go into a cathedral
and the cathedral is a cross by the way
and the cross is the place where
suffering is accepted and the cross is a
dome over it then that's the sky
okay so there's an idea in the Cathedral
and the idea is that the place of the
Cross which is where suffering occurs is
the center of the universe which is the
dome and then you look up at the dome
and you see this figure staring down at
you
that's the king of kings and that's how
to behave in the world that's what that
image represents and you think well what
does it mean well here's a way of
unpacking it and this is associated with
its associated with the idea of how to
behave across the set of all possible
hierarchies well what should you do well
according to rule one you should stand
up straight with your shoulders back
okay now the people who've been some of
the people who've been criticizing me
say well because I point out that
hierarchies exist I'm justifying them
it's like pointing out that something
exists is not the same as justifying it
it's just pointing out that it exists
and pointing it out that it exists
without justifying it is certainly not
saying that the way to attain dominance
in a hierarchy is through power which is
the other thing that I've been
criticized for which is not what I'm
saying in fact I'm not saying that no
I'm not even saying that a little bit
it's exactly the opposite of what I'm
saying say well if you stand up straight
with your shoulders back isn't that a
powerful stance and the answer is well
actually no a powerful stance is this
right well not really because I'm not
very good at it but high if I knew what
I was doing this would be it and I put
myself sideways so I'm ooh not much of a
target and I'm ready for attack okay
that's not this stance this dance is
different right and that isn't this
stance either this is a defensive Crouch
this is what happens if you're depressed
and anxious right this dance is I'm
willing to take what the world throws at
me right and that might be the trials
and tribulations that are associated
with the hierarchy because that's a
tough battle in and of itself but it
also might be all the terrible unknown
things that are going to come your way
and what's the right attitude stand the
hell up
with some courage and take it right
voluntarily with courage so it's
actually a stance of maximal
vulnerability vulnerability adopted
voluntarily that's what the crucifix
represents just so you know it
represents the willingness to take on
the suffering of the world voluntarily
the whole thing and that's associated
with what's ever at the top of the
hierarchy so the idea is the best
possible strategy that you have to be
successful across the set of all
possible hierarchies is to maximally
accept the fact that your vote that
you're vulnerable to accept that as the
price of being and that's the essential
message it's not only the message of
Christianity by the way you see this
sort of idea expressed in all sorts of
religious structures I mean the Daoists
to return to them say well where should
you be in the world the world is made
out of the catastrophe of chaos and the
tyranny of order where do you stand in
that place and the answer is with one
foot in chaos and one foot in order
that's the line down the middle
that's the DAO that's the way that's the
point of meaning it's the same place
that's at the center of a cathedral it's
the same idea you stand there because
you're secure because you have tradition
and the power of your civilization
behind you and you have one foot in
chaos because that's not enough and
never will be and the instinct that puts
you there is the instinct of meaning and
you can use that as a guide and it's a
deep neurological instinct it's not some
epiphenomena it's the most real thing
there is as far as I can tell and
associated with that is a certain
attitude towards life which is to
venture courageously out into the
unknown is to put yourself on the line
right to heed the call of adventure to
risk yourself voluntarily you have no
choice anyways right because you're in
this all the way there's no out that
isn't death the full catastrophe is at
your feet
you can't evade or escape that but what
you can do is choose how it is that
you're going to confront it and so rule
one is to stand up straight with your
shoulders back and to manifest and this
is the thing that's so amazing about
this I think and that what lends a kind
of ultimate reality to the idea of
positioning yourself properly you might
say well let's presume that you're a
very pessimistic person or a very
realistic person and you say well what's
the fundamental reality of life you say
well it's suffering and malevolence it's
like okay it's a hard argument to
forestall but I don't think it's true
it's true but it's not it's not the
final truth the final truth is despite
the fact that that's true the ability of
the human spirit to prevail is more
powerful than death and evil that's the
truth
and you know that you know that first of
all you know that because you're ashamed
that you're not everything you could be
you know that because the people that
you admire are people who manifest
courage in the diarist of straights and
you know that as well because when you
meet people like that and you're not
like that
they shame you that speaks to your
deepest possible instinct you know what
you could be and you know to that you
see people contend with situations that
are so difficult that it's truly a
miracle that they can contend with them
you know and I think of people well I
think of people who work in funeral
homes that's a good example that's hard
right that's death and grief every day
and it's not something that you can
avoid it's like it's right there it's as
real as it can possibly be I'll tell you
a story about that tonight a client who
was very afraid of being alive and she
wanted to sleep all the time and she
took sleeping pills and all sorts of
other things so that she could have
the burden of being conscious and she
was a very good dreamer and she she
wasn't doing well in university and she
had a dream one night that gypsy told
her that she was actually lucid during
her dreams by the way and she could ask
her dream characters what they meant and
they would tell her which was something
I'd never seen anyone else manage in any
case she jumped of this gypsy that she
met in the forest and the Gypsy told her
that unless she learned to unless she
could learn to work in a slaughterhouse
she'd never finished her degree and so
she told me that story no no no if you
know this but the classic treatment for
people who are afraid of things is to
expose them to what they're afraid of
which is a good lesson if you have
children because you want to expose your
children to challenges because that
makes them stronger it has to be done
voluntarily but if you have
post-traumatic stress disorder let's say
you're the victim of a vicious sexual
assault by a stranger and two years
later you have post-traumatic stress
disorder the most effective treatment is
to get you to relive the experience in
as much vivid detail as you possibly can
and experience all the emotions that
occurred while it was happening and if
if you do that the more upset you get
when you do that if you do it
voluntarily the faster you get better
and the longer you stay better and so
it's a general rule of thumb in
psychotherapy is if someone's avoiding
something find out what they're avoiding
break it into manageable pieces and have
them voluntarily expose themselves to it
and they they will be cured and that's
the dragon fight in in clinical practice
find what you most want to what you most
need will be found where you least want
to look right that's a hell of a
statement so she told me this dream and
I thought well I don't know how to
arrange for you to work in a
slaughterhouse that doesn't seem like
very she wouldn't eat meat by the way
she wouldn't go into a butcher store I
took her into a butcher store once and
she had a very catastrophic reaction she
couldn't handle it
anyways I said why we can't arrange the
slaughterhouse thing why don't you go
away and for a while and come back in a
week and see if you can come up with a
No
turn ative so she came back and she said
I want to see an embalming and I thought
oh god okay how the hell am I gonna
arrange that so I phoned a couple of
funeral homes and I said look I've got
this person who's really afraid of death
and she had this dream and I told them
the story and they said no problem bring
her in and so I wasn't looking forward
to this by the way so we went and she
was very very nervous
because she certainly didn't think she
could handle that and you know I as I
said already I wasn't exactly thrilled
about it either but in for a pound in
for a penny in for a pound as they say
so anyways we went to the funeral parlor
and they showed us around and we asked a
bunch of questions like how the hell did
they cope with their jobs because that's
just a mystery to me and they said well
it was actually really useful for them
to guide people through the process of
grief and that their experience was that
that had given them a renewed
appreciation for life which is well that
would account for why they were able to
do it because it seems like a very hard
job and so we went into this room and
watched this embalming and I was about 8
feet away from this small room it's a
pretty gruesome operation as you might
imagine and my client was sitting beside
me and I was watching her and watching
the embalming as well and for the first
while she was just looking to the side
which was I'm not here and I certainly
can't handle that and no bloody wonder
literally and so but then she would take
the odd glance say she'd go like this
and then look away and then as the
minutes ticked by but fairly rapidly she
was spending more time watching and less
time looking away until she was finally
doing nothing but watching and then at
some point she asked if she could come
in and and put her hand on the body and
so they gave her a glove and she did
that and then she went and sat down and
she was quite quiet about all this and
quite quiet afterwards and well so what
did she discover well she didn't
discover the death was wasn't horrible
she didn't discover that and she didn't
discover the death wasn't terrifying
because it certainly was but what she
did discover
that she was a hell of a lot tougher
than she thought and and much quicker
than she would have believed and she
went away thinking huh look at that I
did the thing I was most afraid of doing
and Here I am and not only am I not more
damaged than I was I'm actually better
than I was and so from then on she had a
reference point right which is an
interesting thing I think this is why
primordial people initiate there
especially their young men because it
sort of happens automatically with young
women they expose their young men to
something absolutely terrifying
genuinely terrifying so that for the
rest of their lives they know the
difference between what's actually
terrifying and what's just sort of
normal catastrophe because you really
need to know that right because you need
to know that you can prevail and one of
the things she learned as a consequence
of that exposure was that she could
prevail despite the realities of life of
course that's what you want to teach
your children mostly by example is that
they can prevail
despite the realities of life of course
that also means that you have to have
admitted to what the realities of life
are but the thing that's so interesting
about that here's another story so you
know the story of King Arthur and the
Holy Grail the Holy Grail is the
ultimate value that's it's a symbol of
whatever the ultimate value is and King
Arthur assembles his knights around the
round table it's a round table because
they're all equal despite the fact that
they have a king they sit as equals at
the round table and they all decide to
go off to seek for the Holy Grail
it's either the cup that Christ drank
out about the Last Supper or the cup
that held his blood on the cross it's
one of those two things it doesn't
really matter it's a symbol of what's
redemptive that's what the Holy Grail is
so it's a representation of the ultimate
value the question is where do you go to
seek out what's of ultimate value an
answer in in the tale of the of King
Arthur and the Holy Grail is that each
Knight entered the forest when they
began their search at the place that
looked darkest to them so that's the
thing
is that it's necessary if you're going
to stand up straight with your shoulders
back to confront the darkness of the
world head-on to take responsibility for
the tragedy of existence and for for
malevolence that's what it means that's
the what the Christian injunction to
take the sins of the world onto yourself
means it means it's your bloody problem
and to confront Satan in the desert is
the same idea is that not only do you
have to take on the tragedy of the world
as if it's your responsibility but you
have to contend with the spirit of
malevolence well you're doing so and
it's in doing that that you find your
destiny that's where you find the
highest of possible values and that's
the call and that's the call to the
nobility of being because you might
think well what could possibly justify
your life more thoroughly what could
make you the best player of all possible
games than to take the tragedy of the
world onto your shoulders and to fight
with all your ability against the
malevolence in your own heart thank you
[Applause]
the first one I'll choose here thank you
for coming to speak with us what do you
think of Iceland well first of all thank
you all for coming it's quite remarkable
to see so many people come out for such
a serious conversation it isn't exactly
what you'd expect so everyone has been
ridiculously hospitable to me and my
family we've seen some beautiful things
we were at the Blue Lagoon which was
very impressive we went to the house
today where Gorbachev and Reagan met in
1986 and that was very interesting I
went and saw some rare manuscripts at
the University this morning goon lugar
and his crew of people have been very
organized and you have a beautiful
little capital city that's
extraordinarily impressive and you've
produced this amazing venue and your
country is cruising along on all
cylinders and it's a hell of an
achievement so that's what I think I
think that almost all the time when I
come to a European country it's amazing
how well it works I mean it's a harsh
place you know it's you made a lot of
what you have and it looks to me like
it's just getting better and so it's
peaceful and productive and civilized
and beautiful and hospitable and good
for you and thank you for inviting me
this one the the next one is regards the
hit pieces on you when such an article
is written what is your interpretation
of the course or further what potential
explanations are there for this
phenomenon
well I think there's you know we could
start with what I might be contributing
to it you know one thing I've had to
learn I've had some interactions with
public exposure for probably it's 15
years because I worked a little bit with
a public television station in Ontario
before all this blew up my producer who
is someone who was very much on my side
so I worked for a public affairs show
first of all as a regular panelist and
then as a columnist for a couple of
years my producer was a level-headed guy
well-versed in what worked well in panel
discussions told me to be very careful
about controlling my proclivity towards
anger because it doesn't play very well
publicly and so you know I kept trying
to learn the doctrine of minimal
necessary force I mean I think that
aggression is a good thing if it's
controlled I think it's a good antidote
to fear I think it's one of the things
that can help you maintain your ground
in the face of resistance but it has to
be applied very very judiciously and it
isn't obvious that I always do that as
well as I might and if you're going to
deal with difficult and dangerous and
contentious issues then you're going to
get punished for your failures and so
I'm trying to learn to detach myself and
to not not in that not in and I don't
care away you know but in a watchful way
and to keep all of that under control as
much as possible and to use minimal
necessary force and it's hard to learn
to do that well and so to the degree
that I don't do that then I instigate
more
then I might now I have a hard time with
that to some degree because I do find
some of what I have been let's say
opposing what would you say I'm it makes
me deeply it disturbs me deeply and
makes me unhappy and ashamed that's
particularly the case when I see what's
happening at the universities I'm not
impressed by what's happening in the
social sciences and the humanities I'm
not impressed with the post modernists
I'm not impressed with the Marxists and
I'm certainly not impressed with the
people or the theories that juxtaposed
the two in this particularly ideological
brew that's been fermenting say since
the 1960s and so it's not easy to
maintain equanimity in the face of that
but it doesn't matter because it's still
necessary do you think their ideology
has permeated all of media or because
not all of it
yeah I mean that's the other thing is
that and this is why I dealing now now
we could turn to what the media might
bring to this well ideological or
ideological pre commitments that's
certainly the case an inability to see
anything other than in politicized terms
like I don't view that what I'm doing as
fundamentally political in fact I don't
view the battle that's raging in the
ideon 'el sub structure over Society is
fundamentally political I think it's
deeper than political it's at least
philosophical and it's probably
theological but the but the people
who've been pillory me let's say who
tend to be the postmodern neo-marxist
types or at least lean in that direction
cannot conceptualize anything that isn't
political in their world there isn't
anything that isn't political one of the
things that you might consider for
example is you know I've been perhaps
represented as an
as an advocate of free speech and of
course there's a lot of debate about
what free speech really is from the
radical leftist types and here's
something that you have to understand
from the collectivist perspective that
dominates the radical left there is no
such thing as free speech it's not that
they oppose it it's that it isn't a move
in their game it doesn't exist
so if you stand up and say I'm
manifesting my opinion as an individual
then that's not a acceptable move
because you aren't an individual you're
an avatar of your dominant group and
whatever you utter regardless of why you
think you're uttering it or regardless
of whether you think it's your
individual opinion is nothing but a
power move in your dominance hierarchy
and so it's not like they oppose free
speech it's that it doesn't exist in
their conceptual framework and so that's
one of the things that drives and they
hit pieces because mmm I do believe in
the individual and I do believe in free
speech and I do believe in a world
outside the conceptual realm all sorts
of propositions that aren't part and
parcel of the postmodernist /
neo-marxist game and they're not very
happy with that it's I'm not playing by
the rules and so they don't know what to
do about that the simplest thing to do
is to call me far-right or all right
because then they can first of all
that's an evil category and that
dispenses with that but it also means
they don't have to contend with any of
my arguments and that's convenient so
it's easier to demonize than it is to
contend so it doesn't seem to help them
because the more they scream the more
people that actually listen to you hear
that you're not far right
you're not alright and they stop
believing them well that's the other
thing like I've talked with my wife
about this because it's been in been its
produced
lot of tension are in our family because
it's very stressful I mean for all sorts
of reasons but that's certainly one of
them you know I mean it's certainly not
the case that when I read a head piece
that I'm very pleased about it and I'm
often quite worried about it like the
New York Times piece for example is a
good example and it's idiot what would
you call it
insistence that I was promoting you know
monogamy with the weapons of the state
of all the insane ideas I mean who the
hell believes that it's like some Isis
guys that's about it so so it's an it's
a completely absurd accusation and and
it certainly bore no resemblance to
anything that I meant but you know it's
a powerful media organization and lots
of people warn me in the immediate
aftermath of that that it would be my
downfall including people who were less
they weren't fearful people and so it's
very stressful so one question is well
should I be doing interviews like that
at all because one of the things I
thought is no written interviews only
live interviews only the whole thing so
the one today you had is the last one
well see I don't know because there's
another side of it which is the side you
laid out it's like this happened with
the some of you have seen the Channel 4
interview that I did with Kathy Newman
you know and that was I would say that
was a stressful interview and I would
say that the two weeks after the
interview were also very stressful
because you know first of all there was
the interview and I thought they just
cut it to seven minutes and pillory me
and leave it at that
but they cut it to seven minutes and
pilloried me and then they posted the
whole interview which just shocked me
but here's the shocking thing the people
who posted that interview thought it
went well that's why they posted it they
didn't think oh my god this is
contentious we better put it out believe
me they didn't think that that is not
what they thought they thought it went
fine and so then there was this
overwhelming response to it
and that was completely unexpected and
then the counter response was Peterson's
army of alt-right trolls is victimizing
Kathy Newman and that was that that was
the response of her employers the
technical response because that's what
they published they said we had to call
in police to evaluate the threat it's
like well so what anybody can call in
police to evaluate a threat it doesn't
mean that the threat justified police
intervention or that there was a threat
it just meant that that's how you
responded to it and then they spun a
victim narrative for Kathy which was I
think reprehensible given that I don't
know what Kathy Newman is exactly but
she's not a bloody victim she's not
powerless she's one of the most powerful
women in the United Kingdom and she has
a salary that's commensurate with that
and good good for her that's absolutely
fine but you don't get to have that and
also be a victim it's not the right way
to play the game and so then a whole
bunch of newspapers laid out the story
that poor Kathy was being trolled by my
my legion of all right angry people but
then the numbers started to mount you
know and after it was like four million
people it got the whole troll argument
got hard to sustain unless you think
they were like well now it's perhaps
thirty million people have watched
either the whole thing or major clips
from it maybe it's more than that it's
hard to sustain the old troll argument
when it's thirty million people but it
was very
I thought that narrative was going to
prevail for a while that you know oh she
got victimized and it was all these
terrible people that went after her but
that collapsed but it's very stressful
but and this is something that I've
learned so I've been obsessing about
another statement in the New Testament
for about two years I've been trying to
figure it out and it's it's the
statement that you should turn the other
cheek and that's a tough one man because
well because first of all who wants to
do that because you want to explode in
righteous anger at least you want to
defend yourself you want to do one of
those things so what the hell does that
mean
and partly what it means is if you're
attacked and you're innocent and look
I'm not saying I'm like globally
innocent or anything like that but I'm
not guilty of the accusations that are
levied at me or at least I'm not guilty
in the manner that the accusations would
indicate if you're being attacked and
you're not guilty of the accusations
then the attacks say more about the
attacker than their intended target and
so so far I've been able to withstand
the attacks and the consequence of that
is that it said more about the attackers
than about me and then the question is
can I tolerate that because it's still
very stressful and I very a waver on
that back and forth and then of course
the other issue is is that some people
in the media have pilloried me but many
haven't you know there's been very many
thoughtful people that have written
thoughtful pieces about me there's a
Canadian consortium of 200 newspapers
the post media group and they came out
the entire group came out in favor of my
stance in relationship to Bill c16 in
Canada which was a concern that
compelled speech and so well so
so far in same with the protests when
people come out to protest against me
well the first video that really went
viral was a protest at the University of
Toronto
and after the protest was over that the
the pro the the anti free speech people
at the protests took the microphone away
and and blasted white noise made it
impossible for anyone to speak even
though it was an open mic event so that
got broadcast and then about two hours
after the event I went down to talk to
the cops to see if anybody had been hurt
or anything like that and then on the
way back into the university I got
accosted by half a dozen like radical
types and about thirty of their
hangers-on and then there's a crowd of
people that I would say we're probably
supporting me that that gathered around
me and they went after me and videotaped
all of it on their cell phones and then
they posted that and the idea was that
that was going to do me in but what
happened was the comments were a hundred
to one in favor of what I was saying so
that was another example where the
protests were more damaging to the
protesters than they were to me and
that's been luckily fortunately
miraculously all of that a recurrent
pattern and so the question is whether
or not I can tolerate it and whether my
family can tolerate it and so far look
if you're trying to do something
difficult let's say the right amount of
controversy isn't zero the question is
how much controversy can you handle and
how much of the mud that's thrown will
stick and then how much of it deserves
to stick all of those things you go to
scour your conscience under those
circumstances but so far I've been
fortunate it seems like you've taken on
this track and voluntarily it seems like
from the beginning you've known that
this for example when you spoke up
against Bill c16 in Canada you knew that
this might become tough
well a guide taught people to negotiate
in my clinical practice for a long time
you know I've had lots of clients many
of those clients were female and the the
goal in my consulting with them was to
double or triple their salary within
five years and so that wasn't
necessarily the only goal we discussed
all sorts of goals but that was often
one and so I was very accustomed to
organizing people to negotiate and
there's if you want to negotiate there's
a couple of rules the first rule is you
have to be able to say no and what no
means is there isn't anything you can do
to me to get me to do that that's what
no means no like you can be you can have
different degrees of seriousness about
no but if you're gonna negotiate with
your boss say for a substantial raise no
means if I don't get it then I will
leave that's fundamentally and that
leaving will cost you more than it's not
a threat right it has to be the
observation that me leaving will cost
you substantially more than giving me
the raise you have to be in a position
to make that case or you don't win the
negotiation and so I always put my
clients in a position where if they went
and asked for something they were in a
position to win because we didn't go and
ask before that so when I made the video
criticizing Bill c16 I thought I'm not
abiding by this damn piece of
legislation and then I thought well what
does it mean that I'm not and I thought
well I had multiple sources of income so
I was read I was really the bleep
addition to tolerate a fair bit of
pushback I mean I could have got wiped
out have things gone sideways but it
would have been difficult to take me out
completely and I thought there's no way
I'm biding by this piece of legislation
I was willing I thought through the
negative consequences
now I didn't of course think that any of
this would happen because this is just
completely preposterous and no one could
have possibly foreseen it but so I would
say there were certain things I faced in
doing that but I couldn't have
seen the absolutely explosive
consequences I'm not unhappy that I did
it I would do it again I am still doing
it I suppose so which of your 12 rules
do you break most often I could probably
still be better at listening to people I
like I have these I do interviews with
people I call them discussions because
they're not really interviews probably
they're not interviews because I talk
too much so I had to call them
discussions but I would say the most
common criticism of those discussions is
that I interrupt the people that I'm
discussing things with and and tilt the
conversation probably a little bit more
towards me my thinking than theirs now
part of that I think is my natural
tendency towards like I've always talked
a lot ever since I was like three like
continually
so it's I'm there I'm verbally fluent
you know it's it's part of my nature and
extroverted but you can always get
better at listening you know and so I
can listen and and I practiced that
because I'm a therapist but I would say
that's probably the rule I break that's
rule 9 like assume that the person
you're listening to know something you
don't it's like I'm not as good at that
yet as I could be because I wouldn't get
that criticism if I was like it's not
every comment or anything it's probably
like every xx comment or every xxx
comment but it's but it's still it's
consistent and so every time I have an
interview I think ok I'm gonna try to
shut up a little bit more but then I get
excited about what's happening and you
know and talk too much
one thing related to that sometimes you
seem to go off on a tangent when you're
discussing something you go into
you know something related to it then
you come back to a greater structure of
things do you have you laid all this out
before you say it or do you just go from
one topic to another and they somehow
relate together and become whole and
both yeah but so before I do a talk like
I have to sit I think about the talk all
day before I do it like not a hundred
percent of the time but it's it's in my
mind all the time and what I'm trying to
get is the basic narrative and it's
something like you can only use a
metaphor to really describe it's imagine
you wanted to cross a swamp and there
were stones under the surface you need
to know where the stones are to get from
one side of the swamp to the other and
so then that's what I do in my
imagination I think okay well there's
this area I have to traverse and there's
stepping stones along the way I need to
know where they're located and so that
might be like 12 points or something
like that that's the rough path and then
I have a whole corpus of stories that
fit each of those points and then I can
choose how I'm going to weave those
together but I have to remember where
I'm going and if I'm well like if I'm
healthy and functioning properly then I
can go way out on a tangent and I can
still remember oh yes I have to tie that
back to this point and move to the next
step so it's I like I think it's like
jazz improvisation essentially you know
you have the melody and it has to
organize the melody has to organize all
the improvisation and then I have all
these stories that I know but I every
time I tell this story I try to vary it
so that it brings in something I haven't
brought in before integrate something
you know like what are the things I was
trying to do tonight I've been trying to
figure out for a long time is how to
integrate the idea of the good player of
games with the idea of voluntarily
shouldering your the catastrophe of life
I know those are the same thing but it's
not obvious why and I'm still not
completely obvious to me but I know that
the connection
and I got a fair bit a fair ways tonight
farther than I had it stacking those
concepts on top of each other so the
other thing I'm always trying to do is
to take each of these sets of ideas and
to wave them together more tightly but
also to push them further in their
development so and you've been doing
that on this tour have you been
developing your ideas oh absolutely
absolutely there's you can't give an
effective lecture without so you don't
deliver a talk to an audience first of
all it's not apt talk second you don't
deliver it third it isn't an audience
like all of that's wrong you talk to
individuals in the audience one at a
time and they're representative of the
whole but you're not talking to the
audience if you're afraid of public
speaking it's because you're talking to
the audience it's like forget about that
you just talk to people you know how to
do that and then you're not delivering a
talk because then it's a canned product
you must have just hand people pieces of
paper that they could read it's more
efficient why not do that what you're
doing if you address people properly is
that you involve them in the process of
furthering exploration of important
concepts and you think well how can you
do that because they're sitting there
passively it's like well you're not
passive you're not verbal but you're not
passive like I listen I listen to
whether or not everyone's rustling
around if you're rustling around then
I'm not balancing chaos and order
properly you're not gripped if you're if
I can hear noise in the audience it's
not right I watch people one by one and
I see sometimes they're shaking their
head like this sometimes they're nodding
sometimes they look confused if if
people look confused I think well I
haven't got that right I have to be
watching people and seeing that they're
understanding they're following along
and that indication that they're
following along helps me figure out if
I'm in the right place and so
there's a dynamic that goes along with
it and so all of that and that's what
you're doing if you engage the audience
properly is you shouldn't be talking
about things you don't know enough about
to talk about so if you have to read
your notes it's like sorry you don't
know enough to talk about that because
you need notes now maybe when you're
first starting to talk about something
you need notes but if you need notes you
haven't prepared enough you should know
like ten times as much about the topic
then you're gonna talk about in the talk
otherwise who the hell are you and so
well right I mean you're supposed to be
the authority so you need to know these
things and so and then knowing these
things you want to stretch them further
because when you're this is a theater
and lecture theater theater is drama so
why is it a lecture theater because
lecture is drama what's the drama drama
delivering a talk no there's no drama in
that a tape recorder can do that the
drama is to engage with the ideas
actively in real time and to discover
with the audience what the consequence
is and that's what makes a novel great
for example the reason that Dostoyevsky
novel is great is because Dostoyevsky
did not know where he was going when he
started he had problems you know like
Crime and Punishment is a great example
he wanted to explore the relationship
between crime and punishment
he didn't think well I'm a postmodern
neo-marxist and I have a solution to the
problem of crime and punishment and I'm
gonna write a novel describing what the
right solution is he thought here's a
problem man this is a major problem I'm
gonna divide myself into ten characters
and I'm gonna have a war and I'm gonna
see what prevails and he takes you along
on that voyage and it's that's what
makes Dostoyevsky different than a rant
for example cuz ain't Rand already knew
who the good guys and the bad guys were
and maybe she was right and maybe she
wasn't doesn't matter what matters is
that what she did wasn't literature it
was just sophisticated propaganda you
know like it it taps into literature
upon occasion but but she knew where she
was going whereas Dorsky
dosed
skee he discovered it along the way and
so he takes you along on the journey and
that's any great artist does that takes
you along in the journey that's why it's
so revivifying to encounter anything
that's genuinely artistic is because
you're along for the conflict between
chaos and order and that's way more
interesting than having a talk delivered
to you is it possible that that journey
might lead to a bad place in some cases
you've spoken of Hitler when he was
speaking to audiences and he was
listening to the audiences and that and
he started to find what really engaged
them and made them yeah excited yeah
what he was saying yeah is it possible
that you might get it wrong
oh definitely and it's a terrible threat
to get it wrong because you know in rule
three it's make friends with the people
who want the best for you there are
other rules that were associated with
that that I didn't write about like make
friends with people with oh no let's see
be very careful with who be very careful
about who you shared good news with that
was one rule and another rule was be
very careful about whom you share bad
news with and those are sort of
hallmarks of friendship if you have
friends you can tell good news too you
know what it's like to tell good news to
someone that you shouldn't tell good
news to it's like they're not happy
about your good news they're bitter
about it and and they'll show it in some
way maybe they'll trump your good news
or they won't listen or they'll bring up
another topic or they're secretly angry
or whatever you walk away from sharing
the good news thinking you should have
kept your damn mouth shut and that's not
a good sign and and then but some people
you can tell good news too and they'll
be happy because they have enough sense
to know that life stick catastrophe and
if something good happen to you then
hurray you know because and then bad
news is the same thing it's like if you
tell bad news to someone they need to
let you suffer right they shouldn't make
you feel better quick because they're
upset because you're upset none of that
they just have to take it and that's
hard
so the Oh
I forgot what the hell the question was
here I'm getting tired so I'm losing my
ability to go back where you may get it
wrong when you're interacting with the
audience yes look what Hitler did was
this far as I can tell I've talked to
politicians who've built grassroots
political parties about how they did it
too so the audience talks to you when
you when you deliver when you when you
when you speak publicly they talk to you
with their emotional reactions and then
you can learn how to say what produces a
given emotional reaction especially if
that's what you want if you want say
control over the crowd or maybe you want
you want to harness the anger of the
crowd let's say because your own
motivations what--we're Hitler's
motivations here's the psychoanalytic
answer if you cannot understand the
motivations look at the consequences and
infer the motivation what's the
consequence Hitler blows his brains out
in a bunker under Berlin when Europe is
info on fire what was the motivation a
suicidal apocalypse that's the
motivation how do you generate a
suicidal apocalypse you aim at it how do
you get the crowd to go along you speak
in that manner and you watch for the
emotional response and when you get the
anger that you're after
you facilitate it and you let your
imagination dwell on that and you become
a master of that and that's what Hitler
did and it wasn't like the Germans
weren't angry and they had their reasons
World War one was brutal they lost the
Versailles Treaty was a catastrophe in
the 1920s every decent hard-working
German lost all of their savings in
hyperinflation and the entire country
was threatened by a radical leftist
revolution it was rough and people were
not happy and many of them had been
terribly brutalized by World War one so
there was no shortage of anger to
capitalize on and Hitler was just the
guy annoyed as he was
example that he was rejected from art
school three times despite it despite
having a fair bit of artistic talent he
had his reasons for resentment and and
and hatred and that's just a tiny part
of it yes these things can go terribly
wrong
it depends at least in part on what
you're aiming at people ask me what I'm
aiming at and I would say I mean who
knows right because you don't know
yourself and I don't know myself not to
the final depths but I think what I'm
aiming at I'm hoping is exactly what I
say I'm aiming out I hope that what I'm
aiming at is to tell people stories and
provide them with clinical intervention
information that's derived from the best
literature and science that I know so
that they can be fortified in their
ability to contend with tragedy and
malevolence and the reason that I'm
doing that as far as I'm concerned is
because when I wrote my first book which
was maps of meaning the audio version of
which is out next week by the way I
think it'll be easier to understand
because it's read and the intonation is
all there I concluded after studying the
psychological dynamics of the Cold War
that the only proper medication to
tyrannical collectivism was the
sovereignty of the individual and that
as a consequence that the sovereign
individual needed to be strengthened
that that was the path forward with
least harm and most potential good and I
think that's what I'm doing my evidence
for that is that I've been doing it for
thirty years I taught courses based on
that at Harvard and at the University of
Toronto consistently the lectures were
made into a television program in
Toronto that was popular the lectures
became explosively popular online
everybody can see what I'm saying as far
as I can tell and apart from the hip
pieces which are perhaps valid
criticisms although I don't believe so
the overwhelming evidence as far as I
can tell is that it's having a positive
consequence so and I'm hoping and I have
people watching me and criticizing me
like friends of mine and my family
trying to make sure that this all works
and so hopefully I'm not doing something
that isn't good we'll see but yes so the
last last question what did you think of
the last Star Wars movie I've gone I
don't know if I saw the last Star Wars
movie but I saw one of the last I've
probably seen three of the last and five
Star Wars movies I would say and I
thought they were all the same movie as
the first Star Wars movie so so I
haven't they haven't been my cup of tea
let's say having said that it's obvious
that you know the superhero movies the
Star Wars movies the Star Trek movies
the fantastic success that Marvel in
particular has had with their superhero
Pantheon like those are the most
expensive artifacts that people make a
those movies that's something to really
think about you know people put 200
million dollars into the movie like that
it's not the most expensive thing we
make but it's bloody well up there I can
tell you and it's pretty interesting to
realize as well that making the special
effects for those movies which is which
is a form of artificial reality let's
say is part of what's driving
computational sophistication forward
because the big processors are being
used most intensively to render reality
and so whatever's happening in those
movies is something far more significant
than you might think I think it all
speaks to the unquenchable power of
mythology and its proclivity to manifest
itself in a multitude of forms and and
and to be internally compelling to
people and so generally that seems to be
a really good thing to me so I mean
they're a Harry Potter series
I think is a better example than the
Star Wars series because I think that I
think that the Star Wars series is a bit
too consciously contrived whereas the
Harry Potter series is genuinely to my
way of thinking anyways is a genuine
intuitive production and rolling got her
mythology she's so good at that I just
can't believe it it's just absolutely
unbelievable
and you think of the consequences of
that she wrote with seven books about
wizards like teenage wizards and child
wizards in magical castle threatened by
giant snakes and portrayed the battle
between good and evil on a landscape of
chaos and order and you know sold I
don't know what's her empire worth in
terms of total financial consequences it
would be it's in the tens of billions of
dollars certainly she got all these kids
to read 600 page books they produced all
these movies that were fantastically
expensive everybody read them and went
and watched them it's like and what do
you see there it's a dying and
resurrecting hero fights a satanic
figure and attains final victory through
death and resurrection it's like you
know and it wasn't contrived that came
out of the story and so the mythology
seeps in no matter what and it's I think
and this is something I learned from you
is that it's time for us to understand
it it's we can't just live by it
unconsciously anymore we have to
understand it as well as living by it
and that's the task of the 21st century
that's what it looks like to me so if we
understand it then maybe we can fortify
ourselves against collectivist ideology
for example I'm hoping because that's a
bad pathway so you were able to turn
that question in two very good final
words somehow good so thank you thank
you very much